<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A token for children being an exact account of the conversion, holy and exemplary lives and joyful deaths of several young children / by James Janeway.</title>
            <author>Janeway, James, 1636?-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10750100</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10750100</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45648</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45648)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1405:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A token for children being an exact account of the conversion, holy and exemplary lives and joyful deaths of several young children / by James Janeway.</title>
                  <author>Janeway, James, 1636?-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Children --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Children --  Religious life.</term>
               <term>Children --  Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:1"/>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Three</hi> Books of the ſame Author Mr. <hi>James Janeway,</hi> are Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Newman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>HEaven upon Earth, or the beſt friend in the worſt of times; The third Edition enlarged, Price 2 <abbr>
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Death unſtung,</hi> a Sermon Preacht at the Funeral of <hi>Thomas Mouſley</hi> an <hi>Apothecary:</hi> With a brief Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of his Life and Death: alſo the manner of Gods dealings with Him, before and after his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Drawn up by his own hand; Price 1 <abbr>
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of <hi>Thomas Savage,</hi> Price 4 <abbr>
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:1"/>
                  <p>A TOKEN FOR CHILDREN: BEING An Exact Account of the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Holy and Exemplary Lives, and Joyful Deaths, of ſeveral young Children.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>James Janeway,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>— Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God:</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mark 10.14.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Grocers</hi> Alley in the <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> 1676.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:2"/>
                  <head>To all Parents, School-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and School-Miſtreſſes, or any that have any hand in the Education of Children.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Have oft thought that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks to you, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter did to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Mother; Take this Child and Nurſe it for me. O Sirs, conſider what a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Jewel is committed to your charge, what an advantage you have to ſhew your love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to ſtock the next Generation with Noble Plants, and what a joyful account you may make, if you be faithful: Remember, Souls, Chriſt, and Grace, cannot be over-valued. I confeſs you have ſome diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, but let that only excite your
<pb facs="tcp:45648:3"/>diligence; the Salvation of Souls, the commendation of your Maſter, the greatneſs of your reward, and everlaſting glory, will pay for all. Remember the Devil is at work hard, wicked ones are induſtrious, and a corrupt nature is a rugged knotty piece to hew; but be not diſcouraged, I am almoſt as much afraid of your lazineſs and unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, as any thing. Do but fall to work luſtily, and who knows but that rough ſtone may prove a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in the Temple of God? In the Name of the living God, as you will anſwer in ſhortly at his Bar, I command you to be faithful in Inſtructing and Catechizing your young ones; If you think I am too peremptory, I pray read the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from my Maſter himſelf, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. Is not the duty clear? and dare you neglect ſo direct a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand? Are the Souls of your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of no value? Are you willing
<pb facs="tcp:45648:3"/>that they ſhould be Brands of Hell? Are you indifferent whether they be Damned or Saved? ſhall the Devil run away with them without controul? Will not you uſe your utmoſt endeavour to deliver them from the wrath to come? you ſee that they are not Subjects uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Grace of God; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you think of them, Chriſt doth not ſlight them; they are not too little to dye, they are not too little to go to Hell, they are not too little to ſerve their great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, too little to go to Heaven; <hi>For of ſuch is the Kingdom of God:</hi> And will not a poſſibility of their Converſion and Salvation, put you upon the greateſt diligence to teach them? Or are Chriſt, and Heaven, and Salvation, ſmall things with you? If they be, then indeed I have done with you: but if they be not, I beſeech you lay about you with all your might; the Devil
<pb facs="tcp:45648:4"/>knows your time is going apace, it will ſhortly be too late. O therefore what you do, do quickly; and do it, I ſay, with all your <hi>might;</hi> O pray, pray, pray, and live holily before them, and take ſome time daily to ſpeak a little to your Children, one by one, about their miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Nature; I knew a Child that was converted by this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, from a godly School-miſtreſs in the Country, <hi>Every Mothers Child of you are by Nature Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath.</hi> Put your Children upon Learning their Catechiſm, and the Scriptures, and getting to pray and <hi>weep</hi> by themſelves after <hi>Chriſt:</hi> take heed of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; take heed of pardoning a lye; take heed of letting them miſpend the Sabbath; put them, I beſeech you, upon imitating theſe ſweet Children; let them Read this Book over an hundred times, and obſerve
<pb facs="tcp:45648:4"/>how they are <hi>affected,</hi> and ask them what they think of thoſe Children, and whether they would not be ſuch? and follow what you do with earneſt cries to God, and be in travel to ſee Chriſt formed in their Souls. I have prayed for you, I have oft prayed for your Children, and I love them dearly; and I have prayed over theſe papers, that God would ſtrike in with them, and make them effectual to the good of their Souls. Incourage your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to read this Book, and lead them to improve it. What is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, is faithfully taken from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced ſolid Chriſtians, ſome of them no way related to the Children, who themſelves were Eye and Ear-witneſſes of God's works of Wonder; or from my own knowledg, or from Reverend godly Miniſters, and from Perſons that are of unſpotted reputation for Holineſs, Integrity and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;
<pb facs="tcp:45648:5"/>and ſeveral paſſages are taken <hi>verbatim</hi> in writing from their dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lips. I may add many other excellent Examples, if I have any encouragement in this Piece. That the young generation may be far more excellent than this, is the Prayer of one that dearly loves little Children.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>James Janeway.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:5"/>
                  <head>A PREFACE: Containing <hi>DIRECTIONS</hi> TO CHILDREN.</head>
                  <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> may now hear (my dear Lambs) what other good Children have done, and remember how they wept and prayed by themſelves; how ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly they cryed out for an intereſt in the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> May you not read how dutiful they were to their Parents? How diligent at their
<pb facs="tcp:45648:6"/>Books? how ready to learn the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and their Catechiſms? Can you forget what Queſtions they were wont to ask? How much they feared a lye, how much they abhorred naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty company, how holy they lived, how dearly they were loved, how joyfully they died?</p>
                  <p>But tell me, my dear Children, and tell me truly, Do you do as theſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren did? Did you ever ſee your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate by Nature? Did you ever get by your ſelf and weep for ſin, and pray for grace and pardon? Did you ever go to your Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Maſter, or Miſtreſs, and beg of them to pity you, and pray for you, and to teach you what you ſhall do to be ſaved, what you ſhall do to get Chriſt, Heaven and Glory? Doſt thou love to be taught good things? Come tell me truly, my dear Child; for I would fain do what I can poſſibly to keep thee from falling into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire. I would fain have you one of thoſe little ones, which Chriſt will
<pb facs="tcp:45648:6"/>take into his Arms and bleſs: How doſt thou ſpend thy time? is it in play and Idleneſs, and with wicked Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Dare you take Gods Name in vain, or ſwear, or tell a lie? Dare you do any thing which your Parents forbid you, and neglect to do what they command you? Do you dare to run up and down upon the Lords day? or do you keep in to read your book, and to learn what your good Parents com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you? What do you ſay, Child? Which of theſe two ſorts are you of? Let me talk a little with you, and ask you a few Queſtions.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Were not theſe Children ſweet Children, which feared God, and were dutiful to their Parents? Did not their Fathers and Mothers, and every body that fears God, love them, and praiſe them? What do you think is become of them, now they are dead and gone? Why, they are gone to Heaven, and are ſinging Hallelujahs with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: They ſee glorious things, and having nothing but joy and pleaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:45648:7"/>they ſhall never ſin no more, they ſhall never be beat any more, they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſick, or in pain any more.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> And would not you have your Fathers love; your Mothers Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, your Maſters good word? Would not you have God and Chriſt love you? And would you not fain go to Heaven when you die? And live with your godly Parents in Glory, and be happy for ever?</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Whither do you think thoſe Children go, when they dye, that will not do what they are bid, but play the Truant, and Lye, and ſpeak naughty words, and break the Sabbath? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do ſuch Children go, do you think? Why, I will tell you, they which Lye, muſt go to their Father the Devil into everlaſting burning; they which never pray, God will pour out his wrath upon them; and when they beg and pray in Hell Fire, God will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, but there they muſt lye for ever.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> And are you willing to go to
<pb facs="tcp:45648:7"/>Hell to be burned with the Devil and his Angels? Would you be in the ſame condition with naughty Chilren? O Hell is a terrible place, that's worſe a thouſand times than whipping; Gods anger is worſe than your Fathers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and are you willing to anger God? O Child, this is moſt certainly true, that all that be wicked, and die ſo, muſt be turned into Hell; and if any be once there, there is no coming out again.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Would you not do any thing in the World rather than be thrown into Hell Fire? would you not do any thing in the World to get Chriſt, and grace and glory?</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> Well now, what will you do? will you read this book a little, becauſe your good Mother will make you do it, and becauſe it is a little new Book, but as ſoon as ever you have done, run away to play, and never think of it?</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> How art thou now affected, poor Child, in the Reading of this Book? Have you ſhed ever a tear ſince you
<pb facs="tcp:45648:8"/>begun reading? Have you been by your ſelf upon your knees, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that God would make you like theſe bleſſed Children? or are you as you uſe to be, as careleſs, and fooliſh and diſobedient, and wicked as ever?</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Did you never hear of a little Child that died? and if other Children die, why may not you be ſick and die? and what will you do then, Child, if you ſhould have no grace in your heart, and be found like other naughty children?</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9.</hi> How do you know but that you may be the next Child that may die? and where are you then, if you be not God <hi>'s</hi> Child?</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10.</hi> Wilt thou tarry any longer, my dear Child, before thou run into thy chamber, and beg of God to give thee a Chriſt for thy Soul, that thou mayeſt not be undone for ever? Wilt thou get preſently into a corner to weep and pray? Methinks I ſee that pretty Lamb begin to weep, and thinks of getting by himſelf, and will
<pb facs="tcp:45648:8"/>as well as he can cry unto the Lord, to make him one of theſe little ones that go into the Kingdom of Heaven; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks there ſtands a ſweet Child, and there another, that are reſolved for Chriſt and for Heaven: Methinks that little Boy looks as if he had a mind to learn good things. Methinks I hear one ſay, well, I will never tell a lye more, I will never keep any naughty Boy company more, they will teach me to ſwear, and they will ſpeak naughty words, they do not love God. I'le learn my Catechiſm, and get my Mother to teach me to pray, and I will go to weep and cry to Chriſt, and will not be quiet till the Lord hath given me Grace. O that's my brave Child indeed!</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11.</hi> But will you not quickly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your promiſe? are you reſolved by the ſtrength of Chriſt to be a good child? Are you indeed? nay, but are you indeed? Conſider: dear child,
<pb facs="tcp:45648:9"/>God calls you to remember your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the dayes of your Youth; and he takes it kindly when little ones come to him, and he loves them dearly; and godly people, eſpecially Parents, and Maſters and Miſtreſſes, they have no greater joy, than to ſee their Children walking in the way of truth.</p>
                  <p>Now tell me, my pretty dear Child, What will you do? ſhall I make you a Book? Shall I pray for you, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you? Shall your Good Mother weep over you? And will not you make us all glad, by your turning quickly to the Lord? Shall Chriſt tell you that he will love you? And will not you love him? Will you ſtrive to be like theſe Children? I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that God intends to do good to the Souls of ſome little Chidren by theſe Papers, becauſe he hath laid it ſo much upon my heart to pray for them, and over theſe Papers, and thorow mercy I have already experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, that ſomething of this nature hath not been in vain: I ſhall give a
<pb facs="tcp:45648:9"/>word of direction, and ſo leave you.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Take heed of what you know is naught; as lying, O that is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous fault indeed; and naughty words, and taking the Lords name in vain, and playing upon the Lords Day, and keeping bad company, and playing with ungodly Children: But, if you do go to School with ſuch, tell them that God will not love them, but that the Devil will have them, if they continue to be ſo naught.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Do what your Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bids you, chearfully; and take heed of doing any thing that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid you.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Be diligent in reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and learning your Catechiſm; and what you do not underſtand, to be ſure ask the meaning of.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Think a little ſometimes by your ſelf about God and Heaven, and your Soul, and where you ſhall go when you die, and what Chriſt came into the world for.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> And if you have no great mind
<pb facs="tcp:45648:10"/>to do thus, but had rather be at play, then think what is it that makes me that I do not care for good thinks; is this like one of Gods dear Children? I am afraid I am none of God's Child, I feel I do not love to come to Him: O, what ſhall I do? Either I muſt be Gods Child or the Devils; O, what ſhall I do? I would not be the Devils Child for any thing in the world.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> Then go to your Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or ſome good body, and ask them what thou ſhalt do to be Gods Child; and tell them that thou art afraid, and that thou canſt not be contented, till thou haſt got the love of God.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Get by thy ſelf, into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or Garret, and fall upon thy knees, and weep and mourn, and tell Chriſt, thou art afraid that he doth not love thee, but thou would fain have his love; beg of him to give thee his Grace and pardon for thy ſins, and that he would make thee his Child: Tell God thou doſt not care who don't love thee, if God will but love thee: ſay to him,
<pb facs="tcp:45648:10"/>Father, haſt thou not a bleſſing for me, thy poor little Child? Father, haſt thou not a bleſſing for me, even for me? O give a Chriſt; O give me a Chriſt; O let me not be undone for ever: thus beg, as for your lives, and be not contented till you have an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; and do thus every day, with as much earneſtneſs as you can, twice a day at leaſt.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Give your ſelf up to Chriſt: ſay, dear Jeſus, thou didſt bid that little Children ſhould be ſuffered to come unto thee; and Lord, I am come as well as I can, would fain be thy Child: take my heart, and make it humble, and meek, and ſenſible, and obedient: I give my ſelf to thee, dear Jeſus, do what thou wilt with me, ſo that thou wilt but love me, and give me thy grace and glory.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9.</hi> Get acquainted with godly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ask them good queſtions, and endeavour to love their talk.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10.</hi> Labour to get a dear love for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> read the Hiſtory of Chriſt <hi>'s</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:45648:11"/>ſufferings, and ask the reaſon of his ſufferings; and never be contented till you ſee your need of Chriſt, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and uſe of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11.</hi> Hear the moſt powerful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and read the moſt ſearching Books; and get your Father to buy you <hi>Mr. White's</hi> Book for little Children, and <hi>A Guide to Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12.</hi> Reſolve to continue in well-doing all your dayes; then you ſhall be one of thoſe ſweet little ones that Chriſt will take into his Arms, and bleſs, and give a Kingdom, Crown and Glory to. And now dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, I have done, I have written to you, I have prayed for you; but what you will do, I can't tell. O Children, if you love me, if you love your Parents, if you love your Souls, if you would ſcape Hell Fire, and if you would live in Heaven when you dye, do you go and do as theſe good Children; and that you may be your Parente joy, your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys honour, and live in Gods fear, and dye in his love, is the prayer of your deal Friend.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. Janeway.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45648:11"/>
                  <head>A TOKEN FOR CHILDREN.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="example">
                     <head>
                        <hi>EXAMPLE I.</hi> Of one eminently converted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Eight and Nine years old, with an account of her Life and Death.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>MRS. Sarah Howley,</hi> when ſhe was between eight and nine years old, was carried by her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45648:12"/>Friends to hear a Sermon, where the Miniſter Preached upon <hi>Matthew</hi> 11.30. <hi>My yoak is eaſie, and my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is light:</hi> In the applying of which Scripture, this Child was mightily awakened, and made deeply ſenſible of the condition of her Soul, and her need of a Chriſt; ſhe wept bitterly to think what a caſe ſhe was in; and went home and got by her ſelf into a Chamber, and upon her knees ſhe wept and cryed to the Lord, as well as ſhe could, which might eaſily be perceived by her eyes and countenance.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. She was not contented at this, but ſhe got her little Brother and Siſter into a Chamber with her, and told them of their condition by nature, and wept over them, and prayed with them and for them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. After this ſhe heard another Sermon upon <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.1, <hi>He that being often reproved, hardeneth his heart, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45648:12"/>and that without remedy:</hi> At which ſhe was more affected than before, and was ſo exceedingly ſolicitous about her Soul, that ſhe ſpent a great part of the night in weeping and praying, and could ſcarce take any reſt day or night for ſome time together; deſiring with all her Soul to eſcape from everlaſting flames, and to get an intereſt in the Lord Jeſus; O what ſhould ſhe do for a Chriſt! what ſhould ſhe do to be ſaved!</p>
                     <p n="4">4. She gave her ſelf much to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon the Word Preached, and ſtill continued very tender un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, greatly favouring what ſhe heard.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. She was very much in ſecret prayer, as might eaſily be perceived by thoſe who liſtened at the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Door, and was uſually very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate, and full of tears.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. She could ſcarce ſpeak of ſin, or be ſpoke to, but her heart was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45648:13"/>ready to melt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. She ſpent much time in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture, and a Book called <hi>The beſt Friend in the worſt times;</hi> by which the work of God was much promoted upon her Soul, and was much directed by it how to get acquaintance with God, eſpecially toward the end of that Book. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Book that ſhe was much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with, was Mr. <hi>Swinnocks Chriſtian Mans Calling,</hi> and by this ſhe was taught in ſome meaſure to make Religion her buſineſs. The <hi>Spiritual Bee</hi> was a great companion of hers.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. She was exceeding dutiful to her Parents, very loath to grieve them in the leaſt; and if ſhe had at any time (which was very rare) offended them, ſhe would weep bitterly.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. She abhorred lying, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf in no known ſin.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. She was very Conſcientious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45648:13"/>in ſpending of time, and hated idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſpent her whole time ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in praying, reading, inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her little Brothers, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at her Needle, at which ſhe was very ingenious.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. When ſhe was at School, ſhe was eminent for her diligence, teachableneſs, meekneſs and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, ſpeaking very little; but when ſhe did, it was uſually very ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. She continued in this courſe of Religious Duties for ſome years together.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. When ſhe was about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years old, ſhe brake a Vein in her Lungs (as is ſuppoſed), and oft did ſpit blood, yet did a little recover again, but had ſeveral dangerous relapſes.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. At the beginning of <hi>January</hi> laſt ſhe was taken very bad again, in which ſickneſs She was in great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of Soul. When ſhe was firſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45648:14"/>taken, ſhe ſaid, O Mother, pray, pray, pray, for me, for Satan is ſo buſie that I cannot pray for my ſelf, I ſee I am undone without a Chriſt, and a pardon! O I am undone! un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done to all Eternity!</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Her Mother knowing how ſerious ſhe had been formerly, did a little wonder that ſhe ſhould be in ſuch agonies; upon which her Mother asked her what ſin it was that was ſo burdenſome to her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: O Mother, ſaid ſhe, it is not any particular Sin of Omiſſion or Commiſſion, that ſticks ſo cloſe to my Conſcience, as the Sin of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; without the blood of Chriſt, that will damn me.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Her Mother asked her what ſhe ſhould pray for, for her? ſhe anſwered, that I may have a ſaving knowledg of Sn and Chriſt; and that I may have an aſſurance of Gods love to my Soul. Her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther asked her, why ſhe did ſpeak
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45648:14"/>ſo little to the Miniſter that came to her? She anſwered, that it was her duty with patience and ſilence to learn of them: and it was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing painful to her to ſpeak to any.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. One time when ſhe fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fit, ſhe cried out, O I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I am going: But what ſhall I do to be ſaved? O what ſhall I do to be ſaved? Sweet Lord Jeſus, I will lye at thy feet, and if I periſh, it ſhall be at the Fountain of thy mercy.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. She was much afraid of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and dreaded a miſtake in the matters of her Soul, and would be often putting up ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to God, to deliver her from deceiving her ſelf. To inſtance in one: Great and mighty God, give me faith, and true faith, Lord, that I may not be a fooliſh Virgin, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Lamp and no Oyl.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. She would many times be laying hold upon the Promiſes,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45648:15"/>and plead them in prayer. That in <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28, 29. was much in her Tongue, and no ſmall relief to her ſpirit. How many times would ſhe cry out, Lord, haſt thou not ſaid, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="20">20. Another time her Father bid her be of good cheer, becauſe ſhe was going to a better Father; at which ſhe fell into a great paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſaid, but how do I know that? I am a poor ſinner that wants aſſurance: O, for aſſurance! It was ſtill her Note, O, for aſſurance! This was her great, earneſt, and conſtant requeſt to all that came to her, to beg aſſurance for her; and, poor heart, ſhe would look with ſo much eagerneſs upon them, as if ſhe deſired nothing in the world ſo much, as that they would pity her, and help her with their prayers; never was poor creature
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45648:15"/>more earneſt for any thing than ſhe was for an aſſurance, and the Light of Gods Countenance: O the pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous moan that ſhe would make! O the agonies that her Soul was in!</p>
                     <p n="21">21. Her Mother asks her, if God ſhould ſpare her life, how ſhe would live; truly Mother, ſaid ſhe, we have ſuch baſe hearts that I can't tell; we are apt to promiſe great things; when we are ſick, but when we are recovered, we are as ready to forget our ſelves, and to turn again unto folly; but I hope I ſhould be more careful of my time and my ſoul, than I have been.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. She was full of natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to her Parents, and very careful leaſt her Mother ſhould be tired out with much watching. Her Mother ſaid, how ſhall I bear parting with thee, when I have ſcarce dryed my eyes for thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45648:16"/>She anſwered, The God of love ſupport and comfort you; it is but a little while, and we ſhall meet in Glory, I hope. She being very weak, could ſpeak but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; therefore her Mother ſaid, Child, if thou haſt any comfort, lift up thy hand, which ſhe did.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. The Lords day before that in which ſhe died, a Kinſman of hers came to ſee her, and asking of her, whether ſhe knew him, ſhe anſwered; yes, I know you, and I deſire you would learn to know Chriſt: you are young, but you know not how ſoon you may die; and O to die without a Chriſt, it is a fearful thing: O redeem Time, O Time, Time, Time, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Time! Being requeſted by him not to ſpend her ſelf: ſhe ſaid, ſhe would fain do all the good ſhe could while ſhe lived, and when ſhe was dead too, if poſſible; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which account, ſhe deſired that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45648:16"/>a Sermon might be Preached at the Funeral concerning the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Time. O that young ones would now remember their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour!</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Some Miniſters that came to her, did with earneſtneſs, beg that the Lord would pleaſe to give her ſome token for good, that ſhe might go off triumphing; and Bills of the ſame Nature were ſent to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. After ſhe had long waited for an anſwer of their prayers, ſhe ſaid, <hi>Well, I will venture my ſoul upon Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="26">26. She carried it with wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful patience, and yet would often pray that the Lord would give her more patience, which the Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to aſtoniſhment; for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the pains and agonies that ſhe was in, her patience was next to a wonder; Lord, Lord give me patience, ſaid ſhe, that I may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45648:17"/>not diſhonour thee.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. Upon Thurſday, after long waiting, great fears, and many Prayers, when all her Friends thought ſhe had been paſt ſpeaking, to the aſtoniſhment of her Friends ſhe broke forth thus with a very audible voice, and chearful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: Lord, thou haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that whoſoever comes unto thee, thou wilt in no wiſe eaſt out; Lord, I come unto thee, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou wilt in no wiſe caſt me out. O ſo ſweet! O ſo glorious is Jeſus! O I have the ſweet and glorious Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; he is ſweet, he is ſweet, he is ſweet! O the admirable love of God in ſending Chriſt! O free grace to a poor loſt Creature! And thus ſhe ran on repeating many of theſe things a hundred times over; but her Friends were ſo aſtoniſhed to ſee her in this Divine Rapture, and to hear ſuch gracious words, and her prayers and deſires ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45648:17"/>that they could not write a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of what ſhe ſpoke.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. When her ſoul was thus ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with the love of Chriſt, and her tongue ſo highly engaged in the magnifying of God; her Father, Brethren, and Siſters, with other of the Family were called, to whom ſhe ſpake particularly, as her ſtrength would give leave. She gave her Bible as a Legacy to one of her Brothers, and deſired him to uſe that well for her ſake, and added to him and the reſt, O make uſe of time to get a Chriſt for your Souls; ſpend no time in running up and down in playing; O get a Chriſt for your Souls while you are young, remember now your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor before you come to a ſick-bed; put not off this great work till then, for then you will find it a hard work indeed. I know by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the Devil will tell you it is time enough; and ye are young, what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45648:18"/>need you to be in ſuch haſte? You will have time enough when you are old. But there ſtands one (meaning her Grand-mother) that ſtayes behind, and I that am but young, am going before her. O therefore make your Calling and Election ſure, while you are in health. But I am afraid this will be but one nights trouble to your thoughts; but remmember, theſe are the words of a dying Siſter. O if you knew how good Chriſt were! O if you had but one taſte of his ſweetneſs, you would rather go to him a thouſand times, than ſtay in this wicked world. <hi>I would not for ten thouſand, and ten thouſand worlds part with my intereſt in Chriſt.</hi> O how happy am I that am going to everlaſting Joyes! I would not go back again for twenty thouſand worlds; And will not you ſtrive to get an intereſt in Chriſt?</p>
                     <p n="26">26. After this, looking upon one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45648:18"/>of her Fathers Servants, ſhe ſaid, What ſhall I do? What ſhall I do at that great day, when Chriſt ſhall ſay to me, <hi>Come thou Bleſſed of my Father inherit the Kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thee?</hi> and ſhall ſay to the wicked, <hi>Go thou curſed into the Lake that burns for ever:</hi> What a grief is it to me to think that I ſhall ſee any of my friends that I knew upon Earth turned into that Lake that burns for ever! O that word for ever! Remember that for ever; I ſpeak theſe words to you, but they are nothing, except God ſpeak to you too. O pray, pray, pray, that God would give you grace! and then ſhe prayed, O Lord finiſh thy work upon their Souls. It will be my comfort to ſee you in glory; but it will be your everlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
                     <p n="30">30. Her Grandmother told her ſhe ſpent her ſelf too much; ſhe ſaid, I care not for that, if I could
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45648:19"/>do any Soul good. O with what vehemency, did ſhe ſpeak, as if her heart were in every word ſhe ſpoke.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. She was full of Divine Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and almoſt all her diſcourſe from the firſt to the laſt in the time of her ſickneſs, was about her Soul, Chriſts ſweetneſs, and the Souls of others, in a word, like a continued Sermon.</p>
                     <p n="32">32. Upon <hi>Friday,</hi> after ſhe had had ſuch lively diſcoveries of Gods love, ſhe was exceeding deſirous to die, and cryed out, Come Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, come quickly, conduct me to thy Tabernacle; I am a poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without thee: but Lord Jeſus, my ſoul longs to be with thee: O when ſhall it be? Why not now, dear Jeſus? Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly; but why do I ſpeak thus? Thy time dear Lord is the beſt; O give me patience.</p>
                     <p n="33">33. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> ſhe ſpoke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little (being very drowſie) yet
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45648:19"/>now and then ſhe dropt theſe words, How long ſweet Jeſus, finiſh thy work ſweet Jeſus, come away ſweet dear Lord Jeſus, come quickly; ſweet Lord help, come away, now, now dear Jeſus, come quickly; Good Lord give patience to me to wait thy appointed time; Lord Jeſus help me, help me, help me. Thus at ſeveral times (when out of her ſleep) for ſhe was aſleep the greateſt part of the day.</p>
                     <p n="34">34. Upon the Lords Day ſhe ſcarce ſpoke any thing, but much deſired that Bills of Thanksgiving might be ſent to thoſe who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been praying for her, that they might help her to praiſe God for that full aſſurance that he had given her of his love; and ſeemed to be much ſwallowed up with the thoughts of Gods free love to her Soul. She oft commended her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into the Lords hands, and the laſt words which ſhe was heard to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45648:20"/>ſpeak, were theſe, Lord help, Lord Jeſus help, Dear Jeſus, Bleſſed Jeſus— And thus upon the Lords Day, between Nine and Ten of the Clock in the Forenoon, ſhe ſlept ſweetly in Jeſus, and began an everlaſting Sabbath, <hi>February</hi> 19. 1670.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="example">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45648:20"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>EXAMPLE II.</hi> Of a Child that was admirably affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the things of God, when he was between two and three years Old, with a brief account of his Life and Death.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. A Certain little Child, whoſe Mother had dedicated him to the Lord in the womb: when he could not ſpeak plain, would be crying after God, and was greatly deſirous to be taught good things.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He could not endure to be put to Bed without family duty, but would put his Parents upon duty, and would with much devotion kneel down, and with great pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and delight continue till duty was at an end, without the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of being weary; and he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med never ſo well pleaſed, as when he was engaged in duty.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45648:21"/>
3. He could not be ſatisfied with Family-duty, but he would be oft upon his knees by himſelf in one corner or other.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He was much delighted in hearing the word of God either read or preached.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. He loved to go to School that he might learn ſomething of God, and would obſerve and take great notice of what he had read, and come home and ſpeak of it with much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and he would rejoyce in his book, and ſay to his Mother, O Mother, I have had a ſweet leſſon to day, will you pleaſe to give me leave to fetch my book that you may hear it?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. As he grew up, he was more and more affected with the things of another world, ſo that if we had not received our information from one that is of undoubted fidelity, it would ſeem incredible.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He quickly learned to read
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45648:21"/>the Scriptures, and would, with great Reverence, Tenderneſs and groans read, till tears and ſobs were ready to hinder him.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. When he was at ſecret prayer, he would weep bitterly.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. He was wont often times to complain of the naughtineſs of his heart, and ſeemed to be more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the Corruption of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture than for any actual ſin.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. He had a vaſt Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the things of God, even next to a wonder, for one of his age.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. He was much troubled for the wandrings of his thoughts in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that he could not keep his heart alway fixed upon God, and the work he was about, and his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections conſtantly raiſed.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. He kept a watch over his heart, and obſerved the workings of his Soul, and would complain that the were ſo vain and fooliſh, and ſo little buſied about ſpirituas things.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:45648:22"/>
13. As he grew up, he grew daily in knowledg and experience; and his carriage was ſo heavenly, and his diſcourſe ſo excellent and experimental, that it made thoſe which heard it, even aſtoniſhed.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. He was exceeding importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with God in duty, and would plead with God at a ſtrange rate, and uſe ſuch arguments in prayer that one would think it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ſhould ever enter into the heart of a Child; he would beg and expoſtulate and weep ſo, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it could not be kept from the ears of Neighbours; ſo that one of the next houſe was forced to cry out, the prayers and tears of that Child in the next houſe will ſink me to Hell, becauſe by it he did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn his neglect of prayer, and his ſlight performance of it.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. He was very fearful of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed company, and would oft beg of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45648:22"/>God to keep him from it, and that he might never be pleaſed in them that took delight in diſpleaſing of God: And when he was at any time in the hearing of their wicked words, taking the Lords Name in vain, or ſwearing, or any filthy word, it would even make him tremble, and ready to go home and weep.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. He abhorred lying with his Soul.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. When he had committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fault, he was eaſily convinced of it, and would get in ſome corner and ſecret place, and with tears beg pardon of God, and ſtrength againſt ſuch a ſin. He had a friend that oft watched him, and liſtned at his Chamber-door, from whom I received this Narrative.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. When he had been asked, whether he would commit ſuch a ſin again, he would never promiſe abſolutely, becauſe he ſaid his heart
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45648:23"/>was naught; but he would weep, and ſay, he hoped by the grace of God he ſhould not.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. When he was left at home alone upon the Sabbath days, he would be ſure not to ſpend any part of the day in Idleneſs and Play, but be buſied in praying, Reading in the Bible, and getting of his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. When other Children were playing, he would many a time and oft be praying.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. One day a certain perſon was diſcourſing with him about the Nature, Offices, and Excellency of Chriſt, and that he alone can ſatisfie for our ſins, and merit ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life for us, and about other of the great Myſteries of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: he ſeemed ſavingly to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, and was greatly delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the diſcourſe.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. One ſpeaking, concerning the Reſurrection of the Body, he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45648:23"/>did acknowledg it; but that the ſame weak body that was buried in the Church-yard, ſhould be raiſed again, he thought very ſtrange, but with Admiration yielded, that nothing was impoſſible to God; and that very day he was taken ſick unto death.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. A Friend of his asked him whether he were willing to dye when he was firſt taken ſick; he anſwered, no; becauſe he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of his ſtate as to another world: Why Child, ſaid the other, thou didſt pray for a new Heart, for an humble, and a ſincere Heart, and I have heard thee; didſt thou not pray with all thy heart? I hope I did, ſaid he.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Not long after, the ſame perſon asked him again, whether he were willing to die? He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, now I am willing, for I ſhall go to Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. One asked him what ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45648:24"/>become of his Siſter, if he ſhould die and leave her? He anſwered, the will of the Lord muſt be done,</p>
                     <p n="26">26. He ſtill grew weaker and weaker, but carried it with a great deal of ſweetneſs and patience, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his change; and at laſt did chearfully commit his Spirit unto the Lord, and calling upon the Name of the Lord, and ſaying, Lord Jeſus, Lord Jeſus, — In whoſe boſome he ſweetly ſlept, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as I remember, when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five or ſix years old.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="example">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45648:24"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>EXAMPLE III.</hi> Of a little Girl that was wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when ſhe was between four and five years old; with ſome account of her holy life and triumphant death.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>MAry A.</hi> When ſhe was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween four and five years old, was greatly affected in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word of God, and became very ſolicitous about her Soul and everlaſting condition, weeping bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to think what would become of her in another World, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrange queſtions concerning God and Chriſt, and her own ſoul: ſo that this little <hi>Mary,</hi> before ſhe was full five years old, ſeemed to mind the one thing needful, and to chooſe the better part, and ſat at the feet of Chriſt many a time and oft with tears.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. She was wont to be much in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45648:25"/>ſecret duty, and many times come off from her knees with tears.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. She would chuſe ſuch times and places for ſecret duty, as might render her leſs obſerved by others, and did endeavour what poſſibly ſhe could to conceal what ſhe was doing when ſhe was engaged in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret duty.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. She was greatly afraid of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and of doing any thing to be ſeen of men, and to get commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and praiſe; and when ſhe hath heard one of her Brothers ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he had been by himſelf at prayer, ſhe rebuked him ſharply, and told him how little ſuch prayers were like to profit him, and that was little to his praiſe to pray like a hypocrite, and to be glad that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould know what he had been doing.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Her Mother being full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after the death of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, this Child came to her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45648:25"/>and askt her why ſhe wept ſo exceedingly? her Mother an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, ſhe had cauſe enough to weep, becauſe her Father was dead: No, dear Mother, ſaid the Child, you have no cauſe to weep ſo much, for God is a good God ſtill to you.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. She was a dear lover of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters. One time after ſhe had been hearing of Mr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> ſhe ſaid I love that name dearly for the ſweet words that he ſpeaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Her Book was her delight, and what ſhe did read ſhe loved to make her own, and cared not for paſſing over what ſhe learned without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary obſervations and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and many times ſhe was ſo ſtrangely affected in reading of the Scriptures, that ſhe would burſt out into tears, and would hardly be pacified, ſo greatly was ſhe taken with Chriſts ſufferings, the zeal of Gods Servant, the danger of a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45648:26"/>natural ſtate.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. She would complain often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the corruption of her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of the hardneſs of her heart, that ſhe could repent no more tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, and be no more humble and grieved for her ſins againſt a good God; and when ſhe did thus complain, it was with abundance of tears.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. She was greatly concerned for the ſouls of others, and grieved to think of the miſerable condition that they were in; upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, when ſhe could handſomly, ſhe would be putting in ſome pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſweet word for Chriſt; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, ſhe would do what ſhe could to draw the hearts of her bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſters after Chriſt; and there was no ſmall hopes, that her example and good counſel did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with ſome of them when they were very young to get into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to pray, to ask very gracious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45648:26"/>queſtions about the things of God.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. She was very conſcientious in keeping the Sabbath, ſpending the whole time either in reading or praying, or learning her Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, or teaching her Brethren and Siſters. One time when ſhe was left at home upon the Lords day, ſhe got ſome other little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, together with her brothers and ſiſters, and inſtead of playing (as other naughty children uſe to do) ſhe told them, that that was the Lords day, and that they ought to remember that day to keep it holy; and then ſhe told them how it was to be ſpent in religious exerciſes all the day long, except ſo much as was to be taken up in the works of neceſſity and mercy; then ſhe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them her ſelf, and among other things begged, that the Lord would give grace and wiſdom to them little Children, that they might know how to ſerve him as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45648:27"/>one of the little ones in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with her, told afterwards.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. She was a Child of a ſtrange tenderneſs and Compaſſion to all, full of Bowels and Pity: whom ſhe could not help, ſhe would be ready to weep over; eſpecially if ſhe ſaw her Mother at any time troubled, ſhe would quickly make her ſorrows her own, and weep for her and with her.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. When her Mother had been ſomewhat ſolicitous about any worldly thing, ſhe would, if ſhe could poſſible, put her off from her care one way or other. One time ſhe told her, O Mother, grace is better than that (meaning ſomething her Mother wanted) I had rather have grace and the love of Chriſt, than any thing in the world.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. This Child was often muſing and buſied in the thoughts of her everlaſting Work; witneſs that ſtrange queſtion, O what are they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45648:27"/>doing which are already in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? And ſhe ſeemed to be hugely deſirous to be among them that were praiſing, loving, delighting in God, and ſerving of him without ſin. Her language was ſo ſtrange about ſpiritual matters, that ſhe made many excellent Chriſtians to ſtand amazed, as judging it ſcarce to be paralell'd.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. She took great delight in reading of the Scripture, and ſome part of it was more ſweet to her than her appointed food; ſhe would get ſeveral choice Scriptures by heart, and diſcourſe of them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourly, and apply them ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. She was not altogether a ſtranger to other good Books, but would be reading of them with much affection; and where ſhe might, ſhe noted the Books particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, obſerving what in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding did moſt warm her heart, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45648:28"/>ſhe was ready upon occaſion to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. One time a woman coming into the houſe in a great paſſion, ſpoke of her condition, as if none were like hers, and it would never be otherwiſe; the Child ſaid, it were a ſtrange thing to ſay when its night, it will never be day again.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. At another time a near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of hers being in ſome ſtreights made ſome complaint, to whom ſhe ſaid, I have heard Mr. <hi>Carter</hi> ſay, A man may go to Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Penny in his Purſe; but not without Grace in his heart.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. She had an extraordinary love to the people of God; and when ſhe ſaw any that ſhe thought feared the Lord, her heart would e'n leap for joy.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. She loved to be much by her ſelf, and would be greatly grieved if ſhe were at any time deprived of a coveniency for ſecret duty; ſhe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45648:28"/>could not live without conſtant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to God in ſecret; and was not a little pleaſed when ſhe could go into a corner to pray and weep.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. She was much in praiſing God, and ſeldom or never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of any thing but ſin.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. She continued in this courſe of praying and praiſing of God, and great dutifulneſs and ſweetneſs to her <hi>Parents,</hi> and thoſe that taught her any thing; yea, ſhe did greatly encourage her Mother while ſhe was a Widow, and deſired that the abſence of a Husband might in ſome meaſure be made up by the dutifulneſs and holineſs of a Child. She ſtudied all the ways that could be to make her Mothers life ſweer.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. When ſhe was between Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Twelve years old, ſhe ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in which ſhe carried it with admirable patience and ſweetneſs, and did what ſhe could with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45648:29"/>arguments to ſupport and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage her Relations to part with her that was going to Glory, and to prepare themſelves to meet her in a bleſſed Eternity.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. She was not many days ſick before ſhe was marked; which ſhe firſt ſaw her ſelf, and was greatly rejoyced to think that ſhe was marked out for the Lord, and was now going apace to Chriſt. She called to her Friends, and ſaid, I am marked, but be not troubled, for I know I am marked for one of the Lords own. One asked her how ſhe knew that? She anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Lord hath told me that I am one of his dear Children. And thus ſhe ſpake with a holy confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Lords love to her ſoul, and was not in the leaſt daunted when ſhe ſpake of her death; but ſeemed greatly delighted in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of her nearneſs to her Fathers houſe. And it was not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45648:29"/>long before ſhe was filled with joy unſpeakable in believing.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. When ſhe juſt lay a dying, her Mother came to her and told her ſhe was ſorry that ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and corrected ſo good a child ſo oft. O Mother, ſaid ſhe, ſpeak not thus, I bleſs God, now I am dying, for your reproofs and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections too; for it may be, I might have gone to Hell, if it had not been for your reproofs and correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. Some of her Neighbours coming to viſit her, asked her if ſhe would leave them? She anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, if you ſerve the Lord, you ſhall come after me to glory.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. A little before ſhe died, ſhe had a great conflict with Satan, and cried out, I am none of his; her Mother ſeeing her in trouble, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her what was the matter? She anſwered, Satan did trouble me, but now I think God all is well, I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45648:30"/>know I am none of his, but Chriſts.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. After this, ſhe had a great ſenſe of Gods love, and a glorious ſight, as if ſhe had ſeen the very Heavens open, and the Angels come to receive her; by which her heart was filled with joy, and her tongue with praiſe.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. Being deſired by the ſtanders by to give them a particular account of what ſhe ſaw: ſhe anſwered, you ſhall know hereafter; and ſo in an extafie of joy and holy tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, ſhe went to Heaven, when ſhe was about Twelve years old. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="example">
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:45648:30"/>
                     <head>A Fourth Example of a Child that began to look towards Heaven when ſhe was about four years old, with ſome obſervable paſſages in her Life and at her Death.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. A Certain little Child, when ſhe was about four years old, had a conſcientious ſenſe of her duty towards her Parents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Commandment ſaith, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Father and thy Mother:</hi> And though ſhe had little advantage of education, ſhe carried it with the greateſt reverence to her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents imaginable, ſo that ſhe was no ſmall credit as well as comfort, to them.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It was no unuſual thing for her to weep if ſhe ſaw her Parents troubled, though her ſelf had not been the occaſion of it.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. When ſhe came from School, ſhe would with grief and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45648:31"/>ſay, that other Children had ſinned againſt God by ſpeaking grievous words, which were ſo bad that ſhe durſt not ſpeak them again.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. She would be often times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring of Gods mercy for ſo much goodneſs to her rather than to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that ſhe ſaw ſome begging, others blind, ſome crooked, and that ſhe wanted nothing that was good for her.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. She was many a time and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in one hole or other in tears up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her knees.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. This poor little thing would be ready to counſel other little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren how they ought to ſerve God, and putting them upon getting by themſelves to pray; and hath been known when her friends have been abroad, to have been teaching Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to pray, eſpecially upon the Lords Day.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. She very ſeriouſly begged the Prayers of others, that they would
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45648:31"/>remember her, that the Lord would give her Grace.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. When this Child ſaw ſome that were laughing, who ſhe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be very wicked; She told them, that ſhe feared that they had little reaſon to be ſo merry. They asked whether one might not laugh? She anſwered, no indeed till you have grace, they who are wicked have more need to cry than to laugh.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. She would ſay, that it was the duty of Parents, Maſters and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, to reprove (thoſe under their charge) for ſin, elſe God will meet with them.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. She would be very attentive when ſhe read the Scriptures, and be much affected with them.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. She would by no means be perſwaded to prophane the Lords Day, but would ſpend it in ſome good Duties.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. When ſhe went to School,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45648:32"/>it was willingly and joyfully, and ſhe was very teachable and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary to other children.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. When ſhe was taken ſick, one asked her whether ſhe were willing to die? She anſwered, Yes, if God would pardon her ſins. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked how, her ſins ſhould be pardoned? She anſwered, through the blood of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. She ſaid, ſhe did believe in Chriſt, and deſired, and longed to be with him, and did with a great deal of chearfulneſs give up her ſoul.</p>
                     <p>There were very many obſervable paſſages in the Life and Death of this Child, but the hurry and grief that her friends were in, buryed them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="example">
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:45648:32"/>
                     <head>The Fifth Example of the pious Life and joyful Death of a Child which dyed when he was about twelve years old. <hi>1632.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>CHarles Bridgman</hi> had no ſooner learned to ſpeak, but he betook himſelf to prayer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He was very prone to learn the things of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. He would be ſometimes teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them their duty that waited upon him.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He learned by heart many good things before he was well fit to go to School: and when he was ſet to School, he carried it ſo, that all that obſerved him either did or might admire him. O the ſweet nature, the good diſpoſition, the ſincere Religion which was in this Child!</p>
                     <p n="5">5. When he was at School, what was it that he deſired to learn,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45648:33"/>but Chriſt and him crucified.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. So religious and ſavoury were his words, his actions ſo upright, his devotion ſo hearty, his fear of God ſo great, that many were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay, as they did of <hi>John, What manner of Child ſhall this be?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7. He would be much in reading the holy Scriptures.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. He was deſirous of more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual knowledg, and would be oft asking very ſerious and admirable queſtions.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. He would not ſtir out of doors before he had poured out his Soul to the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. When he eat any thing, he would be ſure to lift up his heart unto the Lord for a bleſſing upon it; and when he had moderately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed himſelf by eating, he would not forget to acknowledg Gods goodneſs in feeding of him.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. He would not lye down in his bed till he had been upon his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45648:33"/>knees; and when ſometimes he had forgotten his duty, he would quickly get out of his bed, and kneeling down upon his bare knees, covered with no Garment but his Linings, ask God forgiveneſs for that ſin.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. He would rebuke his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren if they were at any time too haſty at their meals, and did eat without asking a bleſſing; his check was uſually this; dare you do thus? God be merciful unto us, this bit of bread might choak us.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. His ſentences were wiſe and weighty, and well might become ſome ancient Chriſtian.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. His ſickneſs was a lingring diſeaſe, againſt which, to comfort him, one tells him of poſſeſſions that muſt fall to his portion; and what are they, ſaid he? I had rather have the Kingdom of Heaven than a thouſand ſuch inheritances.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. When he was ſick, he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45648:34"/>much taken up with Heaven, and asked very ſerious queſtions about the nature of his ſoul.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. After he was pretty well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied about that, he enquired how his ſoul might be ſaved; the anſwer being made, by the applying of Chriſts merits by faith; he was pleaſed with the anſwer, and was ready to give any one that ſhould deſire it, an account of his hope.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. Being asked whether he had rather live or dye, he anſwered, I deſire to dye, that I may go to my Saviour.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. His pains encreaſing upon him, one asked him whether he would rather ſtill endure thoſe pains, or forſake Chriſt? Alas, ſaid he, I know not what to ſay, being but a Child, for theſe pains may ſtagger a ſtrong man; But I will ſtrive to endure the beſt that I can. Upon this he called to mind that Martyr <hi>Thomas Bilney;</hi> who
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45648:34"/>being in priſon, the night before his burning put his finger into the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, to know how he could endure the fire. O (ſaid the Child) had I lived then, I would have run through the fire to have gone to Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. His ſickneſs laſted long, and at leaſt three dayes before his death he propheſied his departure, and not only that he muſt dye, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day. On the Lords day, ſaid he, look to me; neither was this a word of courſe, which you may gueſs by his often repetition, every day asking, till the day came indeed, what, is Sunday come? At laſt the lookt-for day came on; and no ſooner had the Sun beautified that morning with its light, but he falls into a trance; his eyes were fixed, his face cheerful, his lips ſmiling, his hands and face claſped in a Bow, as if he would have received ſome bleſſed Angel that were at
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45648:35"/>hand to receive his ſoul: but he comes to himſelf, and tells them how he ſaw the ſweeteſt body that ever eyes beheld, who bid him be of good cheer, for he muſt preſently go with him.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. One that ſtood near him, as now ſuſpecting the time of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution nigh, bid him ſay, Lord into thy hands I commend my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is thy due; for why? thou haſt redeemed it, O Lord my God moſt true.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. The laſt words which he ſpake, were exactly theſe; Pray, pray, pray, nay yet pray, and the more Prayers, the better all proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; God is the beſt Phyſitians, into his hands I commend my ſpirit, O Lord Jeſus receive my ſoul: Now cloſe mine eyes: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me Father, Mother, Brother, Siſter, all the World. Now I am well, my pain is almoſt gone, my joy is at hand, Lord have mercy
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45648:35"/>on me. O Lord receive my Soul un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. And thus he yielded his Spirit up unto the Lord, when he was about twelve years old.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This Narrative was taken out of</hi> Mr. <hi>Ambroſe his Life</hi>'s <hi>Leaſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="example">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:45648:36"/>
                     <head>The ſixth Example of a poor Child that was awakened when ſhe was about five years old.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. A Certain very poor Child that had a very bad Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but it was to be hoped a very good Mother, was by the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God brought to the ſight of a godly friend of mine, who upon the firſt ſight of the Child, had a great pity for him, and took an affection to him, and had a mind to bring him up for Chriſt:</p>
                     <p n="2">2. At the firſt he did with great ſweetneſs and kindneſs allure the Child, by which means it was not long before he got a deep intereſt in the heart of the Child, and he began to obey him with more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than Children uſually do their Parents.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. By this a Door was opened for a farther work, and he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greater
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45648:36"/>advantage to inſtill ſpiritual Principles into the ſoul of the Child, which he was not wanting in, as the Lord gave opportunity, and the Child was capable of.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. It was not long before the Lord was pleaſed to ſtrike in with the ſpiritual Exhortations of this good man, ſo that the Child was brought to a liking of the things of God.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. He quickly learnt a great part of the Aſſemblies Catechiſm by heart, and that before he could read his Primmer within Book; and he took a great delight in learning his Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. He was not only able to give a very good account of his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, but he would anſwer ſuch queſtions as are not in the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, with greater underſtanding than could be expected of one of his age.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He took great delight in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45648:37"/>about the things of God; and when my Friend had been ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praying or reading, expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or repeating of Sermons, he ſeemed very attentive, and ready to receive the truths of God, and would with incredible gravity, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and affection, wait till du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were ended, to the no ſmall joy and admiration of them which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved him.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. He would ask very excellent queſtions, and diſcourſe about the condition of his ſoul and heavenly things, and ſeemed mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned what ſhould become of his ſoul when he ſhould dye, ſo that his diſcourſe made ſome Chriſtians even to ſtand aſtoniſhed.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. He was greatly taken with the great kindneſs of Chriſt in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſinners, and would be in tears at the mention of them; and ſeemed at a ſtrange rate to be affected with the unſpeakable love of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:45648:37"/>
10. When no body hath been ſpeaking to him, he would burſt out into tears; and being asked the reaſon, he would ſay, that the very thoughts of Chriſts love to ſinners in ſuffering for them, made him that he could not but cry.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Before he was ſix years old, he made conſcience of a ſecret du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and when he prayed, it was with ſuch extraordinary meltings, that his eyes have looked red and ſore with weeping by himſelf for his ſin.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. He would be putting of Chriſtians upon ſpiritual diſcourſe vvhen he ſavv them, and ſeemed lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſatisfied; unleſs they vvere talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good things.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Its evident, That this poor Childs thoughts vvere very much buſied about the things of another vvorld, for he vvould oftentimes be ſpeaking to his Bed-fellovv as mid-night, about the matter of his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45648:38"/>ſoul; and when he could not ſleep, he would take heavenly conference to be ſweeter than his appointed reſt. This was his uſual cuſtome, and thus he would provoke and put forward an experienced Chriſtian to ſpend waking hours in talk of God and the everlaſting reſt.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Not long after this, his good Mother died, which went very near his heart, for he greatly honoured his Mother.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. After the dead of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he would often repeat ſome of the promiſes that are made unto Fatherleſs Children, eſpecially that in Exod. 22.22. <hi>Ye ſhall not afflict any Widow or the Fatherleſs Child; if thou afflict them in any wiſe, and they cry at all unto me, I will ſurely hear their cry.</hi> — Theſe words he would often repeat with tears, and ſay, I am Fatherleſs and Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs upon Earth, yet if any wrong me, I have a Father in Heaven who
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45648:38"/>will take my part; to him I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelf, and in him is all my truſt.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Thus he continued in a courſe of holy duties, living in the fear of God, and ſhewed wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful grace for a Child, and died ſweetly in the Faith of Jeſus.</p>
                     <p>My friend is a judicious Chriſtian of many years experience, who was no ways related to him, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant eye and ear-witneſs of his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life, and honourable and chearful death, from whom I received this information.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="example">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:45648:39"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>EXAMPLE VII.</hi> Of a notorious wicked child, who was taken up from begging, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably converted; with an account of his holy Life and joyful Death, when he was nine years old.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. A Very poor Child of the Pariſh of <hi>Newington-Butts</hi> came begging to the door of a dear Chriſtian friend of mine, in a very lamentable caſe, ſo filthy and naſty, that he would even have turned ones ſtomack to have looked on him: But it pleaſed God to raiſe in the heart of my friend, a great pity and tenderneſs towards this poor child, ſo that in Charity he took him out of the ſtreets, whoſe Parents were unknown, who had nothing at all in him to commend him to any ones Charity, but his miſery. My friend eying the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45648:39"/>glory of God, and the good of the immortal ſoul of this wretched Creature, diſcharged the Pariſh of the Child, and took him as his own, deſigning to bring him up for the Lord Chriſt. A noble piece of Charity! And that which did make the kindneſs far the greater was, that there ſeemed to be very little hopes of doing any good upon this Child, for he was a very Monſier of wickedneſs, and a thouſand times more miſerable and vile by his ſin, than by his poverty. He was running to Hell as ſoon as he could go, and was old in naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs when he was young in years; and one ſhall ſcarce hear of one ſo like the Devil in his infancy, as this poor Child was. What ſin was there (that his age was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of) that he did not commit? What by the corruption of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the abominable example of little beggar boyes, he was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45648:40"/>to a ſtrange pitch of impiety. He would call filthy Names, take Gods Name in vain, curſe and ſwear, and do almoſt all kind of miſchief; and as to any thing of God, worſe than an Heathen.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. But his ſin and miſery was but a ſtronger motive to that graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man to pity him, and to do all that poſſibly he could to pluck this fire-brand out of the fire; and it was not long before the Lord was pleaſed to let him underſtand that he had a deſign of everlaſting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon the Soul of this poor child: for no ſooner had this good man taken this creature into his houſe, but he prays for him, and labours with all his might to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of his miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Nature, and to teach him ſomething of God, the worth of his own Soul, and that Eternity of Glory or Miſery that he was born to; and bleſſed be Free-grace, it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45648:40"/>was not long before the Lord was pleaſed to let him underſtand, that it was himſelf which put it into his heart to take in this Child, that he might bring him up for Chriſt. The Lord ſoon ſtruck in with his godly inſtructions, ſo that an amazing change was ſeen in the Child, in a few weeks ſpace he was ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the evil of his ways; no more news now of his calling of Names, Swearing, or Curſing; no more taking of the Lords Name in vain; now he is civil, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful, and ſuch a ſtrange alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was wrought in the child, that all the Pariſh that rung of his vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany before, was now ready to talk of his reformation; his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, his talk, his imployment is now changed, and he is like ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature; ſo that the glory of Gods Free-grace began already to ſhine in him.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And this change was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45648:41"/>an eternal one, and to be diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed abroad, but he would get by himſelf, and weep and mourn bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly for his horrible wicked life, as might eaſily be perceived by them that lived in the houſe with him.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. It was the great care of his godly Maſter to ſtrike in with thoſe convictions which the Lord had made, and to improve them all he could; and he was not a little glad to ſee that his labour was not in vain in the Lord; he ſtill experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that the Lord doth carry on his own work mightily upon the heart of the Child, he is ſtill more and more broken under a ſenſe of his undone ſtate by nature; he is oft in tears and bemoaning his loſt and miſerable condition. When his Maſter did ſpeak of the things of God, he liſtened earneſtly, and took in with much greedineſs and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what he was taught? Seldom was there any diſcourſe about Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45648:41"/>in his hearing, but he heard it as if it were for his life, and would weep greatly.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. He would after his Maſter had been ſpeaking to him or others of the things of God, go to him, and queſtion with him about them, and beg of him to inſtruct and teach him further, and to tell him thoſe things again, that he might remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and underſtand them better.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Thus he continued ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the knowledg of God and Chriſt, and practiſing holy duties, till the ſickneſs came into the houſe, with which the child was ſmitten; at his firſt ſickning, the poor child vvas greatly amazed and afraid, and though his pains were great, and the diſtemper very tedious, yet the ſenſe of his ſin, and the thoughts of the miſerable condition that he feared his ſoul vvas ſtill in, made his trouble ten times greater; he was in grievous agonies of ſpirit, and
<pb facs="tcp:45648:42"/>his former ſins ſtared him in the face, and made him tremble; the poiſon of Gods Arrows did even drink up his ſpirits; the ſenſe of ſin and wrath was ſo great, that he could not tell what in the world to do; the weight of Gods diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the thoughts of lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it to all eternity, did even break him to pieces, and he did cry out very bitterly, what ſhould he do? he was a miſerable ſinner, and he feared that he ſhould go to Hell; his ſins had been ſo great and ſo many that there was no hopes for him. He was not by far ſo much concerned for his life, as for his Soul, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of that for ever. Now the plague upon his body ſeemed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to that which was in his ſoul.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. But in this great diſtreſs the Lord was pleaſed to ſend one to take care for his Soul, who urged to him the great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which were made to one in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45648:42"/>his condition, telling him that there was enough in Chriſt for the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of ſinners, and that he came to ſeek and ſave ſuch a loſt creature as he was. But this poor Child found it a very difficult thing for him to believe that there was any mercy for ſuch a dreadful ſinner as he had been.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. He was made to cry out of himſelf, not only for his ſwearing and lying, and other outwardly notorious ſins; but he was in great horrour for the ſin of his Nature, for the vileneſs of his heart, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal corruption; under it he was in ſo great anguiſh, that the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his ſpirit made him in a great meaſure to forget the pains of his body.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. He did very particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and bewail his ſins with tears; and ſome ſins ſo ſecret that none in the world could charge him with.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. He would condemn himſelf
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45648:43"/>or ſin, as deſerving to have no mercy, though that there was not a greater ſinner in all <hi>London</hi> than himſelf, and he abhorred himſelf as the vileſt creature he knew.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. He did not only pray much with ſtrong cries and tears himſelf, but he begged he prayers of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for him.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. He would ask Chriſtians, whether they thought there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hopes for him, and would beg of them to deal plainly with him, for he was greatly afraid of being deceived.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Being informed how willing and ready the Lord Chriſt was to accept of poor ſinners upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and turning, and being counſelled to venture himſelf upon Chriſt for mercy and ſalvation, he ſaid he would fain caſt himſelf upon Chriſt, but he could not but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how Chriſt ſhould be willing to dye for ſuch a vile wretch as he was;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:45648:43"/>and he found it one of the hardeſt things in the world to believe.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. But at laſt it pleaſed the Lord to give him ſome ſmall hopes that there might be mercy for him, for he had been the chiefeſt of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and he was made to lay a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hold upon ſuch promiſes, as that, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> But O how did this poor boy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and bleſs God for the leaſt hopes! How highly did he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance free and rich grace that ſhould pity and pardon him! and at laſt he was ſo full of praiſe, and admiring of God, ſo that (to ſpeak in the words of a precious man, that was an eye and ear-witneſs) to the praiſe and glory of God be it ſpoken, the houſe at that day, for all the ſickneſs in it, was a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle lower Heaven, ſo full of joy and praiſe.</p>
                     <p n="15">15 The Child grew exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45648:44"/>in knowledg, experiences, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, humility, and ſelf-abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, and he thought he could never ſpeak bad enough of himſelf; the Name that he would call himſelf by, was a Toad.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. And though he prayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet now the Lord poured out upon him the Spirit of prayer in an extraordinary manner, for one of his age; ſo that now he prayed more frequently, more earneſily, more ſpiritually than ever. O how eagerly would he beg to be waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Blood of Jeſus; and that the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, that was over Heaven and Earth, and Sea, would pardon and forgive him all his ſins, and receive his Soul into his Kingdom! and what he ſpoke, it was with ſo much life and fervour of Spirit, as that it filled the hearers with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and joy.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:45648:44"/>
17. He had no ſmall ſenſe of the uſe and excellency of Chriſt, and ſuch longings and breathings of his Soul after him, that when mention hath been made of Chriſt, he hath been ready almoſt to leap out of his bed for joy.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. When he was told that if he ſhould recover, he muſt not live as he liſt; but he muſt give up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Chriſt, and to be his Child and Servant, to bear his Yoke, and be obedient unto his Laws, and live a holy life, and take his Croſs, and ſuffer mocking and reproach, it may be perſecution for his Name ſake. Now Child (ſaid one to him) are you willing to have Chriſt upon ſuch terms? He ſignified his willingneſs by the earneſtneſs of his looks and words, and the caſting up of his eyes to Heaven, ſaying, yes, with all my Soul, the Lord help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, I will do this.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. Yet he had many doubts
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45648:45"/>and fears, and was ever and anon harping upon that, that though he were willing, yet Chriſt he feared was not willing to accept him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the greatneſs of his ſin, yet his hopes were greater than his fears.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. The <hi>Wedneſday</hi> before he died, the Child lay as it were in a trance for about half an hour, in which time he thought he ſaw a Viſion of Angels: When he was out of his Trance, he was in a little pett, and asked his Nurſe, why ſhe did not let him go; go, whither child, ſaid ſhe? why along with thoſe brave Gentlemen (ſaid he): but they told me they would come and fetch me away for all you, upon <hi>Friday</hi> next. And he doubled his words many times, upon <hi>Friday</hi> next, thoſe brave Gentlemen will come for me; and upon that day the Child dyed joyfully.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45648:45"/>
21. He was very thankful to his Maſter, and very ſenſible of his great kindneſs in taking him up out of the ſtreets when he was a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and he admired at the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, which put it into the mind of a ſtranger to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to take ſuch fatherly care of ſuch a pitiful ſorry creature as he was. O my dear Mother (ſaid he) and child of God, I hope to ſee you in Heaven, for I am ſure you will go thither. O bleſſed, bleſſed be God that made you to take pity upon me, for I might have dyed, and have gone to the Devil, and have been damned for ever, if it had not been for you.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. The Thurſday before he dyed he asked a very godly friend of mine, what he thought of his condition, and whither his ſoul was now going? for he ſaid he could not ſtill but fear leaſt he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelf with falſe hopes,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45648:46"/>at which my friend ſpoke to him thus, Child, for all that I have endeavoured to hold forth the grace of God in Chriſt to thy Soul, and given you a warrant from the Word of God, that Chriſt is as freely offered to you, as to any ſinner in the world; if thou art but willing to accept of him, thou mayeſt have Chriſt and all that thou doſt want, with him; and yet thou giveſt way to theſe thy doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and fears, as though I told thee nothing but lyes. Thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou feareſt that Chriſt will not accept of thee; I fear thou art not heartily willing to accept of him. The Child anſwered, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I am: Why then Child, if thou art unfeignedly willing to have Chriſt, I tell thee he is a thouſand times more willing to have thee, and waſh thee, and ſave thee, than thou art to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it. And now at this time
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45648:46"/>Chriſt offers himſelf freely to thee again; therefore receive him hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by Faith into thy heart, and bid him welcome, for he deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it: Upon which words the Lord diſcovered his love to the Child, and he gave a kind of a leap in his bed, and ſnapt his fingers and thumb together with abundance of joy, as much as to ſay, Well, yea all is well, the match is made, Chriſt is willing, and I am willing too; and now Chriſt is mine, and I am his for ever. And from that time forward, in full joy and aſſurance of Gods love, he continued ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly praiſing God, with deſiring to die, and be with Chriſt. And on Friday morning he ſweetly went to reſt, uſing that very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Into thy hands Lord I commit my ſpirit. He died punc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually at that time which he had ſpoke of, and in which he expected
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45648:47"/>thoſe Angels to come to him; he was not much above nine years old when he dyed.</p>
                     <p>This Narrative I had from a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious holy man un-related to him, who was an eye and ear-witneſs to all theſe things.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:48"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:48"/>
                  <p>A TOKEN FOR CHILDREN.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BEING A farther Account of the Converſion, Holy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Lives, and Joyful Deaths of ſeveral other young Children, not publiſhed in <hi>The Firſt Part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>James Janeway,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 8.2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Out of the Mouth of <hi>Babes</hi> and <hi>Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> hoſt thou ordained ſtrength.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Newman,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Grocers Alley</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1673.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:49"/>
                  <head>A PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN the former part of my Tokens for Children, I did in part pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that if that piece met with kind entertainment, it might be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with a ſecond of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If it did not ſeem a little to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of vanity, I might tell the World what encouragement I have met with in this Work; but this I will only ſay, that I have met with ſo much as hath perſwaded me to give this little Book leave to go abroad into the World. I am not alſo ignorant, what Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb facs="tcp:45648:50"/>I may meet with from ſome, but as long as I am ſure I ſhall not meet with this, that it's improbable, if not impoſſible, that it ſhould ſave a Soul; I think the reſt may eaſily be anſwered, or warrantably ſlighted. But becauſe I am perſwaded by ſome, that one Example in the former, (<hi>viz.</hi> that of a Child that began to be ſerious between two and three years old) was ſcarce credible, and they did fear might ſomewhat prejudice the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the reſt, I ſhall ſay ſomething to anſwer that. They which make this Objection are either good or bad; if bad, I expect never to ſatisfie them, except I ſhould tell them of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance or a Play, or ſomewhat that might ſuit a carnal mind, it is like holineſs in older perſons, is a matter of contempt and ſcorn to them, much more in ſuch as theſe I mention. The truth of it is, it is no wonder at all to me, that the Subjects of Satan ſhould not be very well pleaſed with that, whoſe deſign is to undermine the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb facs="tcp:45648:50"/>of their great Maſter: nothing will ſatisfie ſome, except Chriſt and holineſs may be degraded and vilified. But hold ſinner hold, never hope it, Heaven ſhall never be turned into Hell for thy ſake, and as for all thy Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical Objections, Scoffs and Jeers, they ſhall ere long be fully anſwered; and the Hoſannah's and Hallelujah's of theſe Babes ſhall condemn thy Oaths, Blaſphemies, and Jeers, and then thou wilt be ſilenced, and accept conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Grace turn thy heart quickly, thou wilt for ever rue thy madneſs and Folly, when it is too late to remedy it.</p>
                  <p>But if the Perſons that make this Objection be godly, I queſtion not but that I may give them reaſonable ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, conſider who it is that I had that example from. It was one Mrs. <hi>Jeofries</hi> in, <hi>Long-Lane</hi> in <hi>Mary Magdalen Bermondſey</hi> Pariſh, in the County <hi>of Surry,</hi> a woman of that ſame in the Church of Christ, for
<pb facs="tcp:45648:51"/>her exemplary Piety, Wiſdom, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and ſingular watchfulneſs over every punctilio that ſhe ſpeaks; that I queſtion not but that her name is precious to moſt of the Miniſters of <hi>London,</hi> at leaſt in the <hi>Burrough;</hi> and as a reverend Divine ſaid, Such a Mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> her ſingle Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony about <hi>London,</hi> is of as much authority almoſt as any one ſingle Miniſters: And having ſince diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed this matter with her, ſhe calls God to witneſs, that ſhe hath ſpoken nothing but the Truth; only in this ſhe failed, in that ſhe ſpake not by far ſo much as ſhe might have done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that ſweet Babe. I might add, that I have ſince that, ſeen a godly gentleman out of the Countrey, that did profeſs to me, that he had ſeen as much as that in a little one of the ſame age, who ſince that time, I hear, went ſweetly to Heaven. Doth not the Reverend Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> in his Works, quote a Child of two years old that looked towards Heaven?
<pb facs="tcp:45648:51"/>Doth not credible Hiſtory acquaint us with a Martyr at ſeven years old, that was whipped almoſt to death, and never ſhed one tear nor complained, and at laſt had his Head ſtruck off? I do not ſpeak of theſe as common matters, but record them amongſt thoſe ſtupendious Acts of him that can as eaſily work Wonders as not. What is too hard for the Almighty? Hath God ſaid he will work no more wonders? I think moſt of Gods works in the buſineſs of Converſion call for Admiration: And I believe that Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or rather Praiſe would better become Saints, than queſtioning the truth of ſuch things; eſpecially where an apparent Injury is thereby done to the Intereſt of Chriſt, the Honour of Gods Grace, and the Reputation of ſo eminent a Saint. I judge this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſatisfie moſt, as for others I trouble not my ſelf; if I may but promote the intereſt of Chriſt, and the Good of Souls, and give up my Account with joy, it's enough. That
<pb facs="tcp:45648:52"/>the Lord would bleſs my endeavours to theſe ends, I beg the prayers of all Saints, and yours alſo ſweet Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that fear the Lord; and that Parents and Maſters would aſſiſt me with their warm application of theſe things, and that Children may be their Crown and their Joy, is the Prayer of one that deſires to love Chriſt and little children dearly.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>James Janeway,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45648:52"/>
                  <head>A TOKEN FOR CHILDREN.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Second Part.</head>
                  <div n="8" type="example">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Example VIII.</hi> Of a Child that was very ſerious at four years old, with an Account of his comfortable Death when he was twelve years and three weeks old.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>IOhn Sudlow</hi> was born of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Parents in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> whoſe great care was to inſtill ſpiritual Principles into him as ſoon as he was capable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them; whoſe Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the Lord was pleaſed to crown with the deſired ſucceſs; ſo that (to uſe the expreſſion of a holy man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45648:53"/>concerning him) ſcarce more could be expected or deſired from ſo little a one.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. When he was ſcarce able to ſpeak plain, he ſeemed to have a very great awe and reverence of God upon his ſpirit, and a ſtrange ſenſe of the things of another world, as might eaſily be perceived by thoſe ſerious and admirable queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he would be oft asking of thoſe Chriſtians that he thought he might be bold with.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The firſt thing that did moſt affect him, and made him endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to eſcape from the wrath to come, and to enquire what he ſhould do to be ſaved, was the death of a little Brother; when he ſaw him without breath, and not able to ſpeak or ſtir, and then car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of doors, and put into a pit-hole, he was greatly concerned, and asked notable queſtions about him, but that which was moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of himſelf and others, was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45648:53"/>whether he muſt die too, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwered, it made ſuch a deep impreſſion upon him, that from that time forward he was exceeding ſerious and this was when he was about four years old.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Now he is deſirous to know what he might do that he might live in another world, and what he muſt avoid, that he might not die for ever, and being inſtructed by his godly Parents, he ſoon labours to avoid whatſoever might diſpleaſe God; now tell him that any thing was ſinful, and that God would not have him do it, and he is eaſily kept from it, and even at this time of day the apprehenſions of God and Death and Eternity laid ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon him, that he would not for a world have told a Lie.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. He quickly learned to read exactly, and took ſuch Pleaſure in reading of the Scriptures and his Catechiſm, and other good Books, that it is ſcarce to be parallel'd; he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45648:54"/>would naturally run to his Book without bidding, when he came home from School; and while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children of his age and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance were playing, he reckon'd it his Recreation to be doing that which was good.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. When he was in coats, he would be ſtill asking his maid ſerious queſtions, and praying her to teach him his Catechiſm or Scriptures, or ſome good thing; common Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe he took no delight in, but did moſt eagerly deſire to be ſucking in of the knowledge of the things of God, Chriſt, his Soul, and another world.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He was hugely taken with the reading of the Book of Martyrs, and would be ready to leave his Dinner to go to his Book.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. He was exceeding careful of redeeming and improving of time; ſcarce a moment of it, but he would give an excellent account of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of it; ſo that this Child
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45648:54"/>might have taught elder perſons, and will queſtionleſs condemn their idle and unaccountable waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe precious hours in which they ſhould, as this ſweet Child, have been laying in proviſion for Eternity.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. He could not endure to read any thing over ſlightly, but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he read he dwelt upon it, laboured to underſtand it through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and remember it; and what he could not underſtand he would oft ask his Father or Mother the meaning of.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. When any Chriſtian friends have been diſcourſing with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if they began to talk any thing about Religion, to be ſure they ſhould have his company, and of his own accord he would leave all to hear any thing of Chriſt, and creep as cloſe to them as he could, and liſten as affectionately though it were for an hour or two: He was ſcarce ever known to expreſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45648:55"/>the leaſt token of wearineſs while he was hearing any thing that was good, and ſometimes when neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours children would come and call him out, and entice him and beg of him to go with them, he could by no means be perſwaded, though he might have had the leave of his Parents, if he had any hopes that any good body would come in to his fathers houſe.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. He was very modeſt whileſt any ſtranger was preſent, and was loth to ask them any queſtions, but as ſoon as they were gone, he would let his father know that there was little ſaid or done but he obſerved it, and would reflect upon what was paſt in their diſcourſe, and deſire ſatisfaction in what he could not underſtand at preſent.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. He was a Boy of almoſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious parts for his age, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by his ſolid and rational que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions; I ſhall mention but two of many.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45648:55"/>
13. The firſt was this, when he was reading by himſelf in <hi>Draiton</hi>'s Poems about <hi>Noah's</hi> Flood and the Ark, he askt who built the Ark? it being anſwered that it was likely that <hi>Noah</hi> hired men to help him to build it: And would they (ſaid he) build an Ark to ſave another, and not go into it themſelves?</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Another queſtion he put was this; Whether had the greater glory Saints or Angels? It being anſwered, that Angels were the moſt excellent of Creatures, and its to be thought their nature is made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of greater glory than mans. He ſaid he was of another mind, and his reaſon was, becauſe Angles were Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Saints are Children; and that Chriſt never took upon him the nature of Angels, but he took upon him the nature of Saints, and by his being man he hath advanced human nature above the nature of Angels.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. By this you may perceive the greatneſs of his parts, and the bent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45648:56"/>of his thoughts, and thus he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for ſeveral years together, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to get more and more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual knowledge, and to prepare for an endleſs life.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. He was a Child of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſweet temper, wonderful duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to his Parents, ready and joyful to do what he was bid, and by no means would do any thing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe them, and if they were at any time ſeemingly angry, he would not ſtir from them till they were tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly reconciled to him.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. He was not only good him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but would do what he could to make others ſo too, eſpecially thoſe that were neareſt to him; he was very watchful over his brethren and Siſters, and would not ſuffer them to uſe any unhandſome words or to do any unhandſome action, but he would be putting them upon that which was Good, and when he did at any time rebuke them, it was not Childiſhly and ſlightly, but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45648:56"/>with great gravity and ſeriouſneſs, as one that was not a little concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for Gods honour, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal welfare of their Souls.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. He would go to his Father and Mother with great tenderneſs and compaſſion (being far from tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of tales) and beg of them to take more care of the Souls of his brethren and Siſters, and to take heed leaſt they ſhould go on in a ſinful Chriſtleſs ſtate, and prove their ſorrow and ſhame, and go to Hell when they die, and be ruined for ever.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. He was exceedingly affected with hearing of the Word of God preached, and could not be ſatisfied except he could carry home much of the ſubſtance of what he heard; to this end he quickly got to learn Short-hand, and would give a very pretty account of any sermon that he heard.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. He was much engaged in ſecret Duty, and in reading the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45648:57"/>Scriptures; to be ſure morning and evening he would be by himſelf, and was, no queſtion wreſtling with God.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. He would get choice Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by heart, and was very perfect at his Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. The Providences of God were not paſſed by without conſiderable obſervation by him.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. In the time of the Plague he was exceedingly concerned about his Soul and Everlaſting State; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much by himſelf upon his knees. This Prayer was found written in Short-hand after his Death.</p>
                     <q>
                        <p>O Lord God and merciful Father, take pitie upon me a miſerable Sinner, and ſtrengthen me, O Lord, in thy faith, and make me one of thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saints in Heaven. O Lord keep me from this poiſonous Infection, however not my will but thy will be done, O Lord, on earth as it is in heaven, but O Lord, if thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45648:57"/>printed me to die by it, O Lord, fit me for death, and give me a good heart to bear up under my afflictions: O Lord God and merciful Father, take pity on me thy child, teach me O Lord thy Word, make me ſtrong in faith. O Lord I have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, Lord pardon my ſins; I had been in hell long ago if it had not been for thy mercy; O Lord, I pray thee to keep my Parents in thy truth, and ſave them from this Infection, if it be thy will, that they may live to bring me up in the truth: O Lord I pray thee ſtay this Infection that rageth in this City, and pardon their ſins, and try them once more, and ſee if they will turn unto thee. Save me O Lord from this Infection, that I may live to praiſe and glorifie thy name, but O Lord if thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me to die of it, fit me for death, that I may die with comfort; and O Lord, I pray thee to help me to bear up under all afflictions, for Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <p n="24">
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:45648:58"/>
24. He was not a little concerned for the whole nation, and begged that God would pardon the ſins of the Land, and bring it nearer to himſelf.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. About the beginning of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> 1665. this ſweet Child was ſmote with the Diſtemper, but he carried it with admirable pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence under the hand of God.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. Theſe are ſome of his dying Expreſſions. — <hi>The Lord ſhall be my Phyſician, for he will cure both Soul and body.—Heaven is the beſt Hoſpital. —It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth good in his eyes.</hi> Again, —<hi>it is the Lord that taketh away my health, but I will ſay as</hi> Job <hi>did,</hi> Bleſſed be the name of the Lord. — <hi>If I ſhould live longer, I ſhould but ſin againſt God.</hi> Looking upon his Father, he ſaid, <hi>If the Lord would but lend me the leaſt finger of his hand to lead me through the dark entry of Death, I will rejoice in him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="27">27. When a Miniſter came to him, amongſt other things he ſpake
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45648:58"/>ſomewhat of life. He ſaid, <hi>This is a wicked world, yet it is good to live with my Parents, but it is better to live in heaven.</hi> —</p>
                     <p n="28">28. And hour and an half before his Death, the ſame Miniſter came again to viſit him, and asked him, John, <hi>art thou not afraid to die:</hi> He anſwered, <hi>No, if the Lord will but comfort me in that hour.</hi> But ſaid the Miniſter, <hi>How canſt thou expect Comfort, ſeeing we deſerve none?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>No, if I had my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts I had been in hell long ago. But,</hi> replied the Miniſter, <hi>which way doſt thou expect Comfort and Salvation, ſeeing thou art a Sinner.</hi> He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>In Chriſt alone.</hi> — In whom, about an hour and an half after, he fell aſleep, ſaying he would take a long ſleep, charging them that were about him not to wake him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He dyed when he was twelve years three weeks and a day old.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="example">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45648:59"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Example IX.</hi> Of a Child that was very eminent when ſhe was between <hi>5</hi> and <hi>6</hi> years old, with ſome memorable paſſages of her life, who died about <hi>1640.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>ANne Lane</hi> was born of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Parents in <hi>Colebrook</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> who was no ſooner able to ſpeak plain, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs any thing conſiderable of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ſhe began to act as if ſhe was ſanctified from the very womb.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. She was very ſolicitous about her Soul, what would become of it when ſhe ſhould die, and where ſhe ſhould live for ever, and what ſhe ſhould do to be ſaved, when ſhe was about five years old.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. She was wont to be oft ingaged in ſecret Prayer, and pouring out of her Soul in ſuch a manner as is rarely to be heard of from one of her years.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. I having occaſion to lie at <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook</hi> ſent for her Father, an old
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45648:59"/>Diſciple, an Iſraelite indeed, and deſired him to give me ſome account of his Experiences, and how the Lord firſt wrought upon him.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. He gave me this anſwer, that he was of a child ſomewhat civil, honeſt, and as to man harmleſs, but was little acquainted with the power of Religion, till this ſweet Child put him upon a thorow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the ſtate of his Soul, and would ſtill be begging of him, and pleading with him to redeem his time, and to act with life and vigor in the things of God, which was no ſmall demonſtration to him of the reality of inviſibles, that a very Babe and ſuckling ſhould ſpeak ſo feelingly about the things of God, and be ſo greatly concerned not only about her own ſoul, but about her Fathers too, which was the occaſion of his converſion, and the very thought of it was a quickning to him for thirty years, and he hopes never to wear off the Impreſſions of it from his ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45648:60"/>
6. After this ſhe (as I remember) put her Father upon Family duties, and if at any time he were for any time out of his ſhop, ſhe would find him out, and with much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and humility beg of him to come home, and to remember the pretiouſneſs of time, for which we muſt all give an account.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. She was grieved if ſhe ſaw any that converſed with her father if they were unprofitable, unſavoury or long in their diſcourſe of common things.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Her own Language was the Language of <hi>Canaan:</hi> how ſolidly, profitably and ſpiritually would ſhe talk? ſo that ſhe made good people take great delight in her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and juſtly drew the admiration of all that knew her.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. She could not endure the company of common children, nor play, but was quite above all thoſe things which moſt Children are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with; her buſineſs was to be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45648:60"/>reading, praying, diſcourſing, about the things of God, and any kind of buſineſs that her age and ſtrength was capable of, idle ſhe would not be by any means.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. It was the greateſt Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to her to hear any good people talking about God, Chriſt, their Souls, the Scriptures, or any thing that concerned another life.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. She had a ſtrange contempt of the World, and ſcorned thoſe things which moſt are too much pleaſed with. She could not be brought to wear any Laces, or any thing that ſhe thought ſuperfluous.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. She would be complaining to her parents, if ſhe ſaw any thing in them that ſhe judged would not be for the honour of Religion, or ſuitable to that condition which the providence of God had ſet them in, in the world.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. This Child was the joy and delight of all the Chriſtians there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts in thoſe times, who was ſtill
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45648:61"/>quickning and raiſing of the ſpirits of thoſe that talked with her. This poor Babe was a great help to both Father and mother, and her memory is ſweet to this day.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. She continued thus to walk as a ſtranger in the world, and one that was making haſt to a better place. And after ſhe had done a great deal of work for God and her own ſoul, and others too, ſhe was called home to reſt, and received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the arms of Jeſus before ſhe was ten years old; ſhe departed about 1640.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="example">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45648:61"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Example X.</hi> Of a Child that was awakened when ſhe was between ſeven and eight years old, with ſome account of her laſt hours and triumphant Death.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>TAbitha Alder</hi> was the Daughter of a holy and Reverend Miniſter in <hi>Kent,</hi> who lived near <hi>Graveſend.</hi> She was much inſtructed in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and her Catechiſm by her Father and Mother, but there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared nothing extraordinary in her till ſhe was between ſeven and eight years old.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. About which time, when ſhe was ſick, one asked her what ſhe thought would become of her if ſhe ſhould die? She anſwered, that ſhe was greatly afraid that ſhe ſhould go to hell.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Being askt why ſhe was afraid ſhe ſhould go to hell? She anſwered, becauſe ſhe feared that ſhe did not love God.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45648:62"/>
4. Again being askt how ſhe did know ſhe did not love God; ſhe replyed, what have I done for God ever ſince I was born; and beſides this, I have been taught, that he that loves God keeps his commandments but I have kept none of them all.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Being further demanded if ſhe would not fain love God? She an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, yes with all her heart, if ſhe could, but ſhe found it a hard thing to love one ſhe did not ſee.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. She was adviſed to beg of God a heart to love him: She anſwered, ſhe was afraid it was too late.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Being asked again whether ſhe was not ſorry that ſhe could not love God: She anſwered, yes, but was ſtill afraid it was too late.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Upon this, ſeeing her in ſuch a deſponding condition, a dear friend of hers ſpent the next day in Faſting and prayer for her.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. After this, that Chriſtian friend askt her how ſhe did now? She an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with a great deal of joy, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45648:62"/>now ſhe bleſſed the Lord, ſhe loved the Lord Jeſus dearly, ſhe felt ſhe did love him. O, ſaid ſhe, I love him dearly.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Why, ſaith her friend, did you not ſay yeſterday, that you did not love the Lord, and that you could not? What did you mean to ſpeak ſo ſtrangely? Sure (ſaid ſhe) it was Satan that did put it into my mind: But now I love him, O bleſſed be God for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. After this ſhe had a diſcovery of her approaching Diſſolution, which was no ſmall comfort to her. Anon (ſaid ſhe with a holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph) I ſhall be with Jeſus, I am married to him, he is my husband, I am his Bride, I have given my ſelf to him, and he hath given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to me, and I ſhall live with him for ever.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. This ſtrange language made the hearers even ſtand aſtoniſhed: but thus ſhe continued for ſome little time in a kind of extafie of joy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45648:63"/>admiring the excellency of Chriſt rejoycing in her intereſt in him, and longing to be with him.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. After a while ſome of her friends ſtanding by her, obſerved a more than ordinary earneſtneſs and fixedneſs in her countenance; they ſaid one to another, look how earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe looks, ſure ſhe ſeeth ſomething.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. One asked what it was ſhe fixed her eyes upon ſo eagerly: I warrant (ſaith one that was by) ſhe ſeeth death a coming.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. No (ſaid ſhe) it is glory that I ſee, 'tis that I fix mine eye upon.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. One askt her what was glory like? She anſwered, I can't ſpeak what, but I am going to it; will you go with me? I am going to glory, O that all of you were to go with me to that glory! with which words her Soul took wing, and went to the poſſeſſion of that glory which ſhe had ſome believing fight of before. She died when ſhe was between 8 and 9 years old, about 1644.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="example">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45648:63"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Example XI.</hi> Of a Child that was greatly affected with the things of God when ſhe was very young, with an exact Account of her admirable Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age upon her Death bed.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Suſanna Bicks</hi> was born at <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in <hi>Holland, Jan.</hi> 24. 1650. of very religious Parents, whoſe great care was to inſtruct and cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe this their Child, and to preſent her to the Miniſters of the place, to be publickly inſtructed and catechiſed.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It pleaſed the Lord to bleſs holy education, the good example of her Parents and catechiſing, to the good of her Soul, ſo that ſhe ſoon had a true ſavour and reliſh of what ſhe was taught, and made an admirable uſe of it in a time of need, as you ſhall hear afterwards.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. She was a Child of great du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſs to her Parents, and of a very ſweet humble ſpiritual nature,
<pb facs="tcp:45648:64"/>and not only the truth, but the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and eminency of Religion did ſhine in her ſo clearly, that ſhe did not only comfort the hearts of her Parents, but drew the admiration of all that were witneſſes of Gods works of love upon her, and may well be propoſed as a pattern not only to Children, but to perſons of riper years,</p>
                     <p n="4">4. She continued in a courſe of Religious Duties for ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time, ſo that her life was more excellent than moſt Chriſtians, but in her laſt ſickneſs ſhe excelled her ſelf, and her deportment was ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, that partly through won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and aſtoniſhment, and partly through ſorrow, many obſervable things were paſt by without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to paper, which deſerved to have been written in letters of gold: But take theſe which follow as ſome of many which were taken from her dying lips, and firſt publiſhed by religious and judicious Chriſtians
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45648:64"/>in <hi>Dutch,</hi> afterward tranſlated into <hi>Scotch,</hi> and with a little alteration of the ſtile (for the benefit of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Children) brought into this form by me.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. In the month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1664. When the Peſtilence raged ſo much in <hi>Holland,</hi> this ſweet Child was ſmitten, and as ſoon as ſhe felt her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very ill, ſhe was ſaid to break forth with abundance of ſenſe and feeling in theſe following words: <hi>If thy Law were not my delight, I ſhould periſh in my affliction.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. Her Father coming to her to encourage her in her ſickneſs, ſaid to her, be of good comfort my Child for the Lord will be near to thee and us, under this heavy and ſore Trial, he will not forſake us though he chaſten us. Yea, father (ſaid ſhe) our heavenly Father doth Chaſten us for our profit, that we may be partakers of his holineſs; no cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement ſeemeth for the preſent to be joyous, but grievous, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45648:65"/>it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs to them which are exerciſed thereby. The Lord is now chaſtening of me upon this ſick bed, but I hope he will bleſs it ſo to me as to cauſe it to yield to me that bleſſed fruit, according to the riches of his mercies which fail not.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. After this ſhe ſpake to God with her eyes lift up to Heaven, ſaying, Be merciful to me, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be merciful to me a ſinner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy word.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Then looking upon her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Parents, ſhe ſaid; It is ſaid, <hi>Caſt thy burden upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſuſtain thee, and he will never ſuffer the righteous to be moved.</hi> Therefore, my dear father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, caſt all your care upon him who cauſes all things to go well that do concern you.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Her mother ſaid unto her, O my dear child, I have no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the Lord in thee, and the fruit of his grace whereby thou haſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45648:65"/>been ſo much exerciſed unto godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in reading the Word, in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and gracious Diſcourſe, to the edification of thy ſelf and us. The Lord himſelf who gave thee to us, make up this loſs, if it be his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to take thee away from us.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Dear mother (ſaid ſhe) though I leave you and you me, yet God will never leave us; for it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking Child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the fruit of her womb, yet will not I forget thee, behold I have graven thee upon the palms of my hands.</hi> O com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable words both for mother and children! Mark, dear Mother, how faſt the Lord keepes and holdeth his people, that he doth even grave them upon the palms of his hands. Though I muſt part with you, and you with me, yet bleſſed be God, he will never part either from you or me.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Being weary with much ſpeaking ſhe deſired to reſt a while,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45648:66"/>but after a little time awaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, her father asked her how it was with her? She made no direct anſwer, but asked what day it was? her father ſaid it was the Lords day. Well then, ſaid ſhe, have you given up my name to be remembred in the publick Prayers of the Church: Her father told her he had. I have learnt, ſaid ſhe, that the effectual fervent Prayer of the righteous avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. She had a very high eſteem for the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, and much deſired their company where ſhe was; but knowing the hazards that ſuch a viſit might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them and the Church to, ſhe would by no means ſuffer that the Miniſters ſhould come near her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but choſe rather to throw her ſelf upon the armes of the Lord, and to improve that knowledge ſhe had in the Word, and her former expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and the viſits of private Chriſtians, and thoſe which the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45648:66"/>Church had appointed in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to viſit and comfort the ſick.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. One of thoſe which came to viſit her, was of very great uſe to her to comfort her, and lift her up in ſome meaſure above the fears of death.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Though young, ſhe was very much concerned for the intereſt of God and Religion, for Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and for the Sins and the Decay of the power of Godlineſs in her own Countrey; which will further appear by what may follow.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Her father coming in to her, found her in an extraordinary paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of weeping, and askt her what was the cauſe of her great ſorrow? She anſwered, have I not cauſe to weep, when I hear that <hi>Domine de Wit</hi> was taken ſick this day in his Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; and went home very ill? Is not this a ſad ſign of Gods diſpleaſure to our Countrey, when God ſmiteth ſuch a faithful Paſtor.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. She had a high valuation of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45648:67"/>God, and could ſpeak in <hi>David's</hi> language, <hi>whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none on earth that I can deſire in compariſon of thee.</hi> She was much lifted up above the fears of Death; what elſe was the meaning of ſuch expreſſions as theſe? <hi>O how do I long! even as the Heart panteth after the water brooks, ſo my ſoul panteth after thee, O God, for God, the living God, when ſhall I come and appear before God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="17">17. She was a great hater of ſin, and did with much grief and ſelf-abhorrency reflect upon it; but that which lay moſt upon her heart was the Corruption of her Nature and Original Sin. How oft would ſhe cry out in the words of the Pſalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt, <hi>Behold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my mother conceive me, and I was altogether born in ſin:</hi> She could never lay her ſelf low enough under a ſenſe of that Original Sin which ſhe brought with her into the world.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:45648:67"/>
18. She ſpake many things very judiciouſly of the old man and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it off, and of the new man and putting that on; which ſhewed that ſhe was no ſtranger to conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and that ſhe in ſome meaſure underſtood what Mortification, Self-denial and taking up of her Croſs, and following of Chriſt meant. That Scripture was much in her mouth, <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a contrite heart; a broken and a contrite ſpirit, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> That brokenneſs of heart (ſaid ſhe) which is built upon and flows from faith, and that faith which is built upon Chriſt, who is the proper and alone Sacrifice for Sin. Theſe are her own words.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. Afterwards ſhe deſired to reſt, and when ſhe had ſlumbred a while, ſhe ſaid, O dear father and Mother, how weak do I feel my ſelf! My dear Child (ſaid her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) God will in his tender mercy ſtrengthen thee in thy weakneſs.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45648:68"/>Yea father (ſaid ſhe) that is my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence: For it is ſaid, <hi>The bruiſed reed he will not break, and the ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king flax he will not quench.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="20">20. Then ſhe diſcourſed excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently of the nature of Faith, and deſired that the eleventh of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> ſhould be read unto her; at the reading of which ſhe cryed out, O what a ſtedfaſt loyal faith was that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which made him willing to offer up his own and only Son! Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. Her Father and Mother hearing her excellent diſcourſe, and ſeeing her admirable carriage, burſt out into abundance of tears: upon which ſhe pleaded with them to be patient and content with the hand of God. O (ſaid ſhe) why do you weep at this rate over me, ſeeing, I hope you have no reaſon to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but if the Lord take me out of this miſerable world it ſhall be well
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45648:68"/>with me to all eternity. You ought to be well ſatisfied, ſeeing it is ſaid <hi>God is in heaven, and doth whatſoever pleaſeth him:</hi> and do you not pray every day, that the Will of God may be done upon earth as it is in heaven. Now farther this is Gods will that I ſhould lie upon this ſick bed, and of this diſeaſe; ſhall we not be content when our Prayers are anſwered? Would not your extreme ſorrow be murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, without whoſe good pleaſure nothing comes to paſs. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am ſtruck with this ſad diſeaſe, yet becauſe it is the will of God, that doth ſilence me, and I will as long as I live pray that Gods will may be done and not mine.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Seeing her Parents ſtill very much moved, ſhe further argued with them from the Providence of God, which had a ſpecial hand in every common thing, much more in the diſpoſal of the lives of men and women: <hi>Are not two Sparrows
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45648:69"/>ſold for a farthing, and not one of them falls to the ground without our heavenly Father?</hi> Yea, <hi>the hairs of our head are all numbred; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fear not, you are of more value than many Sparrows.</hi> Adverſity and Proſperity they are both good. Some things ſeem evil in our eyes, but the Lord turns all to the good of them which are his.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. She came then to ſpeak par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly concerning the Plague, Doth not (ſaid ſhe) the Peſtilence come from God; why elſe doth the Scripture ſay, <hi>ſhall there be evil in the City which I have not ſent?</hi> What do thoſe people mean, which ſay the Peſtilence comes from the Air? Is not the Lord the Creator and Ruler of the Air, and are not the Elements under his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Or if they ſay it comes from the Earth, hath he not the ſame power and influence upon that too? What talk they of a Ship that came from <hi>Africa;</hi> have we not read long
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45648:69"/>ago together out of <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.25. <hi>I ſhall bring a ſword upon you, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the quarrel of my covenant, and when you are aſſembled in the Cities, then will I bring the peſtilence in the midſt of you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="24">24. After this, having taken ſome little reſt, ſhe ſaid, O now is the day for the opening of the firſt queſtion of the Catechiſm, and if we were there, we ſhould hear, that whether in death or life a Believer is Chriſts, who hath redeemed us by his own precious blood from the power of the Devil; and then ſhe quoted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.7, 8. <hi>For none of us liveth unto himſelf, and none of us dieth to himſelf. For whether we live we live unto the Lord, and whether we die we die unto the Lord, whether then we live or die, we are the Lords.</hi> Then be comforted, for whether I live or die, I am the Lords, O why do you afflict your ſelves thus? but what ſhall I ſay? with weeping I came into the world, and with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45648:70"/>weeping I muſt go out again. O my dear Parents, better is the day of my death than the day of my birth.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. When ſhe had thus encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her Father and Mother, ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her Father to pray with her, and to requeſt of the Lord that ſhe might have a quiet and peaceable paſſage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another world.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. After her father had prayed for her, he asked her whether he ſhould ſend for the Phyſician; ſhe anſwered, by no means, for I am now beyond the help of Doctors. But ſaid he, my Child, we are to uſe the ordinary means appointed by the Lord for our help as long as we live, and let the Lord do as ſeemeth good in his eyes. But ſaid ſhe, give me the heavenly Phyſician he is the only helper, doth not he ſay, <hi>Come unto me ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give ye reſt,</hi> and doth not he bid us call upon him in the day of diſtreſs, and he will deliver us, and we ſhall glorifie him:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45648:70"/>Therefore, dear father, call upon him yet again for me.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. About this time a Chriſtian friend came in to viſit her, who was not a little comforted when he heard and ſaw ſo much of the grace of God living in a poor young thing, which could not but ſo far affect him as to draw tears of joy and admiration from him, and her deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſo teaching, that he could not but acknowledg himſelf greatly edifi'd and improv'd by her carriage and language.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. That which was not the leaſt obſervable in her, was the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent affection ſhe had for the holy Scriptures and her Catechiſm, in which ſhe was throughly inſtructed by the godly Divines of the place where ſhe lived which ſhe could not but own as one of the greateſt mercies next the Lord Chriſt. O how did ſhe bleſs God for her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and beg of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to go particularly to thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that had taken ſo much pains with her to inſtruct her in her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and to thank them from her a dying Child for their good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45648:71"/>and to let them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, for their encouragement to go on in that work of Catechiſing. how refreſhing thoſe truths were now to her in the hour of her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. O that ſweet catechiſing, ſaid ſhe, unto which I did always reſort with gladneſs, and attended without wearineſs!</p>
                     <p n="29">29. She was much above the vanities of the world, and took no pleaſure at all in thoſe things which uſually take up the heart and time of young ones. She would ſay, that ſhe was grieved and aſhamed both for young and old, to ſee how glad and mad they were upon vanity. and how fooliſhly they ſpent their time.</p>
                     <p n="30">30. She was not forgetful of the care and love of her Maſter and Miſtreſs which taught her to read and work, but ſhe deſired that thanks might alſo be particularly given to them. Indeed ſhe thought ſhe could never be thankful enough
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45648:71"/>both to God and man for that kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that ſhe had experience of: But again and again ſhe deſired to be ſure to thank the Miniſters that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed her either by catechiſing or preaching.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. After ſome reſt her Father askt her again how ſhe did, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to expreſs ſomewhat of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and joy that he had taken in her former diligence in her read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures and writing, and her dutifulneſs, and that great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs that ſhe had made in the things of God, upon which ſhe humbly and ſweetly deſired to own God and his kindeſs in her godly education, and ſaid that ſhe eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her holy education under ſuch Parents and Miniſters as a greater portion than ten thouſand Gilders, for thereby I have learned to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſelf out of the Word of God, which the World beſides could never have afforded.</p>
                     <p n="32">32. Her Father perceiving her to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45648:72"/>grow very weak, ſaid, I perceive Child thou art very weak: It is true Sir (ſaid ſhe) I feel my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs increaſeth, and I ſee your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row increaſing too, which is a piece of my affliction; be content, I pray you, it is the Lord which doth it, and let you and I ſay with <hi>David, Let us fall into the Lords hands, for his mercies are great.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="33">33. She laid a great charge upon her Parents not to be over-grieved for her after her death, urging that of <hi>David</hi> upon them, while the Child was ſick, he faſted and wept, but when it died, he waſhed his face and ſat up and eat, and ſaid, <hi>Can I bring him back again from death, I ſhall go to him but he ſhall not return to me.</hi> So ought you to ſay after my death, our Child is well, for we know it ſhall be well with them that truſt in the Lord. She did lay a more particular and ſtreight charge upon her mother; ſaying to her, dear mother, who
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45648:72"/>have done ſo much for me, you muſt promiſe me one thing before I die; and that is, that you will not ſorrow over-much for me: I ſpeak thus to you, becauſe I am afraid of your great affection; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider others Loſſes what they have been; Remember <hi>Job;</hi> forget not what Chriſt foretold; <hi>In the world you ſhall have tribulation, but be of good cheer in me you ſhall have peace;</hi> and muſt the Apoſtles ſuffer ſo great tribulation, and muſt we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer none? Did not Jeſus Chriſt my only Life and Saviour ſweat drops of blood? Was he not in a bitter agony, mocked ſpit at, nailed to the Croſs, and a Spear thruſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his bleſſed ſide, and all this for my ſake, for my ſtinking ſins ſake? did not he cry out, <hi>my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Did not Chriſt hang naked upon the Croſs to purchaſe for me the garments of ſalvation, and to cloth me with his righteouſneſs, for there
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45648:73"/>is Salvation in no other name.</p>
                     <p n="34">34. Being very feeble and weak, ſhe ſaid, O if I might quietly ſleep in the boſome of Jeſus! and that till then he would ſtrengthen me! O that he would take me into his arms as he did thoſe little ones, where he ſaid, <hi>Suffer little children to come unto me, for of ſuch is the kingdom of heaven, and he took them into his arms, and laid his hands on them and bleſſed them.</hi> I lie here as a child, O Lord I am thy Child, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me into thy gracious arms. O Lord, grace! grace! and not juſtice, for if thou ſhouldeſt enter into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with me, I cannot ſtand, yea none living ſhould be juſt in thy ſight.</p>
                     <p n="35">35. After this ſhe cryed out, O how faint am I! but fearing leaſt ſhe ſhould diſhearten her mother, ſhe ſaid, while there is life there is hope: If it ſhould pleaſe the Lord to recover me, how careful would I be to pleaſe you in my work and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45648:73"/>learning, and whatſoever you ſhould require of me.</p>
                     <p n="36">36. After this the Lord did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſend her ſtrength, and ſhe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to ſpend it all for Chriſt in the awakening, edifying and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting of thoſe that were about her; but her chiefeſt endeavour was to ſupport her dear Parents from extraordinary ſorrow, and to comfort them out of the Scriptures, telling them that ſhe knew that <hi>all things did work together for the good of them that did love God, even to thoſe which are called according to his purpoſe; O God eſtabliſh me with thy free Spirit! Who ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us from the love of Chriſt, I am perſwaded that neither life nor death, nor angels, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent nor things to come, nor heighth nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall ſeparate us from the love of God which is towards us in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. My ſheep</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>hear my voice,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45648:74"/>and I know them and they follow me and I give unto them eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, and no man ſhall pluck them out of my hands. My Father who gave them me is greater than all, and none ſhall pull them out of my Fathers hands.</hi> Thus ſhe ſeemed to attain a holy confidence in God, and an aſſurance of her ſtate as to another world.</p>
                     <p n="37">37. When ſhe had a little refreſhed her ſelf with reſt, ſhe burſt forth with abundance of joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, with a holy triumph of faith ſaying out, Death is ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up of victory, <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the law, but thanks be to God who hath given us the victory through our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="38">38. That ſhe might the better ſupport her friends, ſhe ſtill inſiſted upon that which might take off ſome of their burden, by urging the neceſſity of death: <hi>We are from the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45648:74"/>earth and to the earth we muſt return: is the mother of us all, the duſt ſhall Duſt turn to duſt from whence it is, and the Spirit to God which gave it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="39">39. The She diſcourſed of the ſhortneſs of mans life. O what is the life of man! <hi>the days of man upon the earth are as the graſs and the flowers of the field, ſo he flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the wind paſſeth over it and it is no more, and his place knows him no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="40">40. She further urged the ſin and ſorrow that did attend us in this life, and the longer we live the more we ſin, now the Lord will free me from that ſin and ſorrow. We know not the thoughts of God, yet we do know ſo much, that they are mercy and peace, and to give an expected end. But what ſhall I ſay, my life ſhall not continue long, I feel much weakneſs, O Lord look upon me graciouſly, have pitie upon my weak diſtreſſed heart. I am oppreſſed, undertake for me, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45648:75"/>I may ſtand faſt and overcome.</p>
                     <p n="41">41. She was very frequent in ſpiritual ejaculations, and it was no ſmall comfort to her, that the Lord Chriſt did pray for her, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſend his ſpirit to comfort her, It's ſaid (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter.</hi> O let not him leave me! O Lord, continue with me till my battel and work be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
                     <p n="42">42. She had very low and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing thoughts of her ſelf and her own reighteouſneſs; what meant ſhe elſe to cry out in ſuch language as that, None but Chriſt! without thee I can do nothing. Chriſt is the true vine! O let me be a branch of that vine! What poor worms are we! O dear Father, how lame and halting do we go in the wayes of God and Salvation. We know but in part, but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is imperfct ſhall be done away. O that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45648:75"/>I had attained to that now: But what are we of our ſelves? not only weakneſs and nothingneſs, but wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs. For all the thoughts and imaginations of mans heart are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evil, and that continually; we are by nature children of wrath, and are conceived and born in ſin and unrighteouſneſs. Oh! Oh! this wretched and vile thing Sin! but thanks be to God who hath redeemed me fromit.</p>
                     <p n="43">43. She comforted her ſelf and her Father in that great Scripture <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16, 17. <hi>Ye have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Spirit of bondage again to fear but ye have received the ſpirit of adoption by which ye cry Abba, father. It is the ſpirit that witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with our ſpirits, that we are the children of God; and if Children, then are we heirs, heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ.</hi> You ſee thence father, that I ſhall be a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low heir with Chriſt, who hath ſaid, <hi>In my fathers houſe are many
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45648:76"/>manſionſ, if it were not ſo I would have told you, I go to prepare a place for you, and if I go to prepare a place for you, I will come again and take you to my ſelf, that where I am there ye may be alſo.</hi> O Lord take me to thy ſelf. Behold, dear Mother, he hath prepared a place and dwelling for me.</p>
                     <p n="44">44. Yea, my dear child, ſaid her mother, he ſhall ſtrengthen you with hiſ holy Spirit, untill he hath fitted and prepared you fully for that place which he hath prepared for you.</p>
                     <p n="45">45. Yea Mother, it is ſaid in the 84. Pſalm, <hi>How lovely are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts, my ſoul doth thirſt, and longeth for the Courts of the Lord: One day in thy Courts iſ better than a thouſand; yea, I had rather be a Door keeper in the houſe of God than dwell in the tents of the wicked.</hi> Read that Pſalm, dear Mother, therewith we may comfort one another. As for me, I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45648:76"/>am more and more ſpent, and draw near my laſt hour.</p>
                     <p n="46">46. Then ſhe deſired to be pray'd with, and begged that the Lord would give her an eaſie paſſage.</p>
                     <p n="47">47. After this, ſhe turned to her mother, and with much affection ſhe ſaid, Ah my dear and loving Mother; that which cometh from the heart doth ordinarily go to the heart, once more come and kiſs me before I leave you.</p>
                     <p n="48">48. She was not a little concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the ſouls of the reſt of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and did particularly charge it upon her father to do what he could poſſibly to bring them up in the ways of God. O let my ſiſter be trained up in the Scriptureſ and Catechiſing, as I have been.</p>
                     <p n="49">49. I formerly wept for my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, thinking that ſhe ſhould die before me, and now ſhe weepeth for me, and then ſhe kiſſed her weeping Siſter. Alſo ſhe took her young little Siſter in her arms, a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45648:77"/>Child of ſix months old, and ſhe kiſſed it with much affection, as if her very bowels had moved within her, and ſpoke with many heart-breaking words both to her Parents and the children.</p>
                     <p n="50">50. Her Father ſpake to one that was by to take the poor little Child away from her, from the hazard of that fiery diſtemper, and bid his daughter to give her from her, for he had already too much to bear. Well Father, ſaid ſhe, did not God preſerve the three Children in the fiery furnace, and did not you teach me that Scripture, <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the Fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="51">51. She had a very ſtrong Faith in the doctrine of the Reſurrection, and did greatly ſolace her Soul with excellent Scriptures, which do ſpeak the happy ſtate of Believers as ſoon as their Souls are ſeparated from their Bodies, and what ſhe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45648:77"/>quoted out of the Scripture ſhe did excellently and ſuitably apply to her own uſe, incomparably above the common reach of her ſex and age. That in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42. was a great ſupport to her, <hi>The body is ſown in corruption, but it ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, it is ſown in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, it ſhall be raiſed in glory; it is ſown in weakneſs, but it ſhall be raiſed in power.</hi> And then ſhe ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applies it, and takes in this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial. Behold thus it is, and thus it ſhall be with my poor mortal fleſh, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, becauſe they reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them. The righteous periſh and no man layeth it to heart, and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right are taken away, and no man regardeth it, that they are taken away from the evil to come, they ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds, every one who walked in their up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs.</hi> Behold now Father I ſhall reſt and ſleep in that Bedchamber.</p>
                     <p n="52">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:45648:78"/>
52. Then ſhe quoted <hi>Job</hi> 19.25, 26, 27. <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter end upon the earth, and though after my skin worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God, whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and my eyes ſhall behold, and net another, though my reins be conſumed within me.</hi> Behold now Father, this very skin which you ſee, and this very fleſh which you ſee, ſhall be raiſed up again; and theſe very eyes which now are ſo dim, ſhall on that day ſee and behold my dear and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Redeemer; albeit the worms eat up my fleſh, yet with theſe eyes ſhall I behold God, even I my ſelf, and not another for me.</p>
                     <p n="53">53. Then ſhe quoted <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28: <hi>Marvel not at this, for the hour is coming in which all that are in their graves ſhall hear his voice and come forth, thoſe who have done good unto the Reſurrection of Life.</hi> See Father I ſhall riſe in that day, and then I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45648:78"/>ſhall behold my Redeemer; then ſhall he ſay, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you before the beginning of the world.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="54">54. <hi>Behold now I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the life that I now live in the fleſh is by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me and gave himſelf for me. I am ſaved, and that not of my ſelf, it is the gift of God, not of works, that no man ſhould boaſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="55">55. My dear Parents, now we muſt ſhortly part, my ſpeech faileth me, pray the Lord for a quiet cloſe to my combat.</p>
                     <p n="56">56. Her Parents replied, Ah our dear child how ſad is that to us that we muſt part! She anſwered, I go to heaven, and there we ſhall find one another again, I go to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="57">57. The ſhe comforted her ſelf to think of her ſeeing her precious brother and ſiſter again in glory.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45648:79"/>I go to my brother <hi>Jacob,</hi> who did ſo much cry and call upon God to the laſt moment of his breath: And to my little ſiſter, who was but three years old when ſhe died: who when we asked her whether ſhe would die; anſwered, yes, if it be the Lords will. I will go to my little Brother, if it be the Lords will, or I will ſtay with my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it be the Lords will. But I know that I ſhall die and go to heaven, and to God. O ſee, how ſo ſmall a babe had ſo much given it to behave it ſelf every way, and in all things ſo ſubmiſſively to the will of God, as if it had no will of its own; but if it be the will of God, if it pleaſe God, nothing for her, but what was the will and pleaſure of God: And therefore, dear Father and Mother, give the Lord thanks for this his free and rich grace, and then I ſhall the more gladly be gone. Be gracious then, O Lord, unto me alſo, be gracious
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45648:79"/>to me. Waſh me thorowly from my unrighteouſneſs, and cleanſe me from my ſin.</p>
                     <p n="58">58. After this her ſpirit was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with the ſenſe of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of her Sins, which made her to cry out, Behold God hath waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away my ſins, O how do I long to die! The Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>In this body we earneſtly ſight and groan, longing for our houſe which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that we may be clothed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</hi> Now I alſo lie here ſighing and longing for that dwelling which is above. In the laſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon which I heard, or ever ſhall hear, I heard this in the New Church, which is matter of great comfort unto me.</p>
                     <p n="59">59. Then ſhe repeated ſeveral notable Scriptures which were quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that Sermon, afterward ſhe deſired to be pray'd with, and put petitions into their mouths, <hi>viz</hi> that all her ſins might be forgiven, that ſhe might have more abundant
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45648:80"/>faith, and the aſſurance of it; and the comfort of that aſſurance, and the continuation and ſtrength of that comfort, according as her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity ſhould require. Afterwards ſhe prayed her ſelf and continued a pretty ſpace.</p>
                     <p n="60">60. When Prayer was ended, ſhe called to her father and mother, and demanded of them whether ſhe had at any time angred or grieved them, or done any thing that did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her? and begged of them to forgive her.</p>
                     <p n="61">61. They anſwered her, that if all children had carried themſelves ſo to their Parents as ſhe had done, there would be leſs grief and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row on all hands than there is; and if any ſuch thing hath eſcaped thee, we would forgive it with all our hearts, you have done as became a good Child.</p>
                     <p n="62">62. Her heart being quieted with her peace with God and her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſhe began to diſpoſe of her
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45648:80"/>Books; particularly ſhe intreated her Mother to keep Mr. <hi>De Wit's</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſe Lectures as long as ſhe lived, for her ſake, and let my little Siſter have my other Book as my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
                     <p n="63">63. Then ſhe ſaid ſhe felt her breaſt exceedingly pained, by which ſhe knew that her end was very nigh. Her father ſpake to her as he was able, telling her the Lord would be her ſtrength in the hour of her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
                     <p n="64">64. Yea (ſaid ſhe) <hi>The Lord is my Shepherd, although I paſs through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will not fear, for thou art with me, thy rod and thy ſtaff they comfort me:</hi> and it is ſaid, <hi>the ſufferings of this preſent life are not worthy to be compared with the glory that ſhall be revealed in us.</hi> Shall I not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and indure, ſeeing my glorious Redeemer was pleaſed to ſuffer ſo much for me. O how was he mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and crowned with thorns that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45648:81"/>he might purchaſe a Crown of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for us: And that is the crown of which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke, when he ſaid, <hi>I have fought the good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith, henceforth is laid up for me a crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give unto me in that day; and not only to me, but to all who love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prearing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="65">65. <hi>Ye are bought with a price<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore Glorifie God with your ſouls and bodies which are his.</hi> Muſt I not then exalt and bleſs him while I have a being; who hath bought me, ye bought me with his blood? <hi>Surely he hath born our griefs, and took our infirmities; and we eſteemed him ſmitten and ſtricken of God: But he was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions and bruiſed for our ſin, the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and by his ſtripes are we healed, and the Lord laid upon him the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of us all. Behold the Lamb of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45648:81"/>God that taketh away the ſins of the world:</hi> That Lamb is Jeſus Chriſt who hath ſatisfied for my ſins. So ſaith <hi>Paul, Ye are waſhed, ye are ſanctified, ye are juſtified in the name of our Lord Jeſus, and through the ſpirit of our God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="66">66. My end is now very near, now I ſhall put on white raiment and be clothed before the Lamb, that ſpotleſs Lamb, and with his ſpotleſs righteouſneſs. Now are the angels making ready to carry my ſoul before the throne of God. <hi>Theſe are they who are come out of great tribulation, who have waſhed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="67">67. She ſpoke this with a dying voice, but full of ſpirit and of the power of faith.</p>
                     <p n="68">68. Her lively aſſurance ſhe further uttred in the words of the Apoſtle. <hi>We know that if this earthly houſe, if our tabernacle be diſſolv'd, we have one which is built of God, which is eternal
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45648:82"/>in the heavens; for in this we ſigh for our houſe which is in heaven, that we may be clothed therewith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="69">69. There Father you ſee that my body is this Tabernacle which now ſhall be broken down; my Soul ſhall now part from it, and ſhall be taken up into the heavenly Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, into that heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> There ſhall I dwell and go no more out, but ſit and ſing, <hi>Holy, holy, holy is the Lord God of hoſts, the Lord of Sabbaths!</hi> Her laſt words were theſe; O Lord God into thy hands I commit my ſpirit, O Lord be gratious, be merciful to me a poor ſinner. — And here ſhe fell aſleep.</p>
                     <p n="70">70. She died the firſt of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1664. Betwixt ſeven and eight in the evening, in the fourteenth year of her age; having obtained that which ſhe ſo oft intreated of the Lord, a quiet and eaſie depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the end of her faith, the ſalvation of her ſoul.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="example">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:45648:82"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Example XII.</hi> Of the excellent carriage of a Child upon his death bed when but ſeven years old.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IAcoh Bicks,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſannah Bicks,</hi> was born in <hi>Leiden</hi> in the year, 1657. and had religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous education under his godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the which the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſanctifie to his Converſion, and by it lay in excellent proviſions to live upon in an hour of diſtreſs.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This ſweet little Child was viſited of the Lord of a very fore Sickneſs upon the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1664. three or four weeks before his Siſter, of whoſe life and death we have given you ſome account al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: in his diſtemper he was for the moſt part very ſleepy and drouſie till near his death, but when he did wake he was wont ſtill to fall a praying.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Once when his Parents had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45648:83"/>prayed with him, they asked him if they ſhould once more ſend for the Phyſician? No (ſaid he) I will have the Doctor no more; the Lord will help me: I know he will take me to himſelf, and then he ſhall help all.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Ah my dear child, ſaid his Father, that grieveth my heart: Well (ſaid the Child) Father let us pray, and the Lord ſhall be near for my helper.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. When his Parents had prayed with him again, he ſaid, come now dear Father and Mother and kiſs me, I know that I ſhall die.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Farewell dear Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Farewell dear ſiſter, farewell all. Now ſhall I go to heaven unto God and Jeſus Chriſt, and the holy angels: Father, know you not what is ſaid by <hi>Jeremiah: Bleſſed is he who truſteth in the Lord:</hi> now I truſt in him, and he will bleſs me. And in 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. it is ſaid, <hi>Little Children love not the world, for the world paſſeth away.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:45648:83"/>
7. Away then all that is in the world, away with all my pleaſant things in the world: away with my Dagger for where I go there is nothing to do with Daggers and Swords; men ſhall not fight there but praiſed God. Away with all my books; there ſhall I know ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and be learned in all things of true wiſdom without books.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. His Father being touched to hear his child ſpeak at this rate could not well tell what to ſay; but, my dear child, the Lord will be near thee and uphold thee.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Yea Father (ſaid he) the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, but he giveth grace to the humble.</hi> I ſhall humble my ſelf under the mighty hand of God, and the ſhall help and lift me up:</p>
                     <p n="10">10. O my dear child, ſaid his Father, haſt thou ſo ſtrong a faith?</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Yea, ſaid the Child, God hath given me ſo ſtrong a faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf through Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45648:84"/>that the Devil himſelf ſhall flee from me, for it is ſaid, <hi>He who believeth in the Son hath everlaſting life, and he hath overcome the wicked one.</hi> Now I believe in Jeſus Chriſt my Redeemer, and he will not leave or forſake me, but ſhall give unto me eternall life, and then I ſhall ſing, <hi>holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of Sabbath.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">12. Then with a ſhort word of Prayer, Lord be merciful to me a poor ſinner, he quietly breathed out his Soul, and ſweetly ſlept in Jeſus when he was about ſeven years old. He died <hi>Auguſt</hi> 8. 1664.</p>
                     <closer>Hallelujah.</closer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="example">
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:45648:84"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Example XIII.</hi> Of one that began to look towards Heaven, when he was very young, with many eminent paſſages of his life, and his joyful death, when he was eleven years and three quarters old.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Iohn Harvy</hi> was born in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in the year 1654. His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a Dutch Merchant, he was piouſly educated under his virtuous mother, and ſoon began to ſuck in divine things with no ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The first thing very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in him was, that when he was two years and eight months old, he could ſpeak as well as other children do uſually at five years old.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. His Parents judging that he was then a little to young to ſend out to ſchool, let him have his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45648:85"/>liberty to play a little about their yard, but inſtead of playing, he found out a ſchool of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord hard by home, and went to the ſchool-Miſtriſs, and intreated her to teach him to read, and ſo he went for ſome time to ſchool without the knowledge of his Parents, and made a very ſtrange progreſs in his learning, &amp; was able to read diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before moſt Children are able to know their letters.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He was wont to ask many ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and weighty queſtions about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which concerned his ſoul and Eternity.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. His Mother being greatly troubled upon the death of one of his Uncles, this Child came to his Mother, and ſaid; Mother, though my Uncle be dead, doth not the Scripture ſay, he muſt riſe again; yea, and I muſt die, and ſo muſt every body, and it will not be long before Chriſt will come to judge the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45648:85"/>world and then we ſhall ſee one another again, I pray Mother do not weep ſo much. This grave Counſel he gave his Mother, when he was not quite five years old, by which her ſorrow for her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was turned into admiration at her Child, and ſhe was made to ſit ſilent and quiet under that ſmarting ſtroke.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. After this, his Parents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to <hi>Aberdeen</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſetled their Child under an able and a painful School Maſter there, whoſe cuſtome was upon the Lords day in the morning, to examine his ſchollers concerning the Sermons that they had heard the former Lords day, and to add ſome other queſtions which might try the underſtanding and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Schollers; the queſtion that was once propoſed to his form was, whether God had a mother? none of all the Schollars could anſwer it, till it came to <hi>John Harvy,</hi>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:45648:86"/>who being asked, whether God had a Mother, anſwered no; as he was God, he could not have a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but as he was man, he had; this was before he was quite ſix years old. His Maſter was ſomewhat amazed at the Childs answer, and took the firſt opportunity to go to his Mother, to thank her for inſtructing her Son ſo well, but ſhe replyed, that he was never taught that from her, but that he underſtood it by reading, and his own obſervation.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He was a Child that was extraordinary inquiſitive, and full of good queſtions, and very careful to obſerve and remember what he heard.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. He had a great hatred of whatſoever he knew to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, and was ſo greatly concerned for the honour of God, that he would take on bitterly, if that any groſs ſins were committed before him. And he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45648:86"/>had a deep ſenſe of the worth of Souls, and was not a little grieved when he ſaw any one do that which he knew was dangerous to their Souls.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. One day ſeeing one of his near Relations come into his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe diſtemper'd with drink as he thought, he quickly went very ſeriouſly to him and wept over him, that he ſhould ſo offend God, and hazard his Soul, and beg'd of him to ſpend his time better then in drinking and gaming, and this he did, without any inſtruction from his parents, but from an inward principle of grace, and love to God and ſouls as it is verily believed.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. When he was at play with other Children, he would be often times putting in ſome word to keep them from naughty talk, or wicked actions, and if any did take the Lords name in vain, or do any thing that was not becoming of a good Child, they ſhould ſoon hear of it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45648:87"/>with a witneſs; nay once hearing a boy ſpeak very profanely, and that after two or three admonitions, he would not forbear nor go out of his company neither, he was ſo tranſported with zeal, that he could not forbear falling upon him to beat him; but his Mother chiding of him for it, he ſaid, that he could not indure to hear the name of God so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by a wretched boy. This is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved not to vindicate the act, but to take notice of his zeal.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. He was a Child that took great delight in the Company of good men, and eſpecially, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Schollers; and if he had any leiſure time, he would improve it by viſiting of ſuch, whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe might make him wiſer and better; and when he was in their ſociety, to be ſure, his talk was more like a Chriſtian and Scholler, then a Child.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. One day after School time was over, he gave <hi>Mr. Andrew
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45648:87"/>Kant.</hi> (one of the Miniſters of <hi>Aberdeen</hi>) a viſit, and asked him ſeveral ſolid queſtions, but the good man asked him ſome queſtions out of his Catechiſm: and finding him not ſo ready in the anſwers as he ſhould have been, did a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him, and told him, that he muſt be ſure to get his Catechiſm perfectly by heart; the Child took the reproof very well, and went home and fell very hot upon his Catechiſm, and never left, till he got it by heart, and not only ſo, but he would be enquiring into the ſenſe and meaning of it.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. He was ſo greatly taken with his Catechiſm, that he was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to learn it himſelf but he would be putting others upon learning their Catechiſm, eſpecially, thoſe that were neareſt to him; he could not be ſatisfied, till he had perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Mothers Maids to learn it, and when they were at work, he would be ſtill following them with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45648:88"/>ſome good queſtion or other; ſo that the Child ſeemed to be taken up with the thoughts of his Soul and Gods honour, and the good of others Souls.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. He was a conſcientious obſerver of the Lords day, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the time either in ſecret prayer, or reading the Scriptures, and good books; Learning of his Catechiſm, and learning of the Word of God, and publick duties; and was not only careful in the performance of theſe duties himſelf, but was ready to put all that he knew upon a ſtrict obſervation of the Lords day; and was exceedingly grieved at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of it; one Lords day a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of his Fathers going out of the houſe upon an extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to fetch ſome Beer, he took on ſo bitterly, that he could ſcarce be pacified, becauſe that holy day was ſo abuſed (as he judged) in his fathers houſe.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. When he was betwixt ſix
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45648:88"/>and ſeven years old, it pleaſed God to afflict him with ſore eyes which was no ſmall exerciſe to him, becauſe it kept him from School which he loved as well as many boys do their play, and that which was worſe, he was commanded by the Doctor not to read any Book whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, at home. But, O how was this poor Child grieved, that he might not have liberty to read the holy Scriptures; and for all their charge, he would get by himſelf, and ſtand by the windows, and read the Bible and good Books; yea he was ſo greedy of reading the Scripture, and took so much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it, that he would ſcarce allow himſelf ſometimes time to dreſs himſelf for reading, the Word of God was his great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Yea, though he hath been bear for ſtudying ſo much, yet judging it Gods command that he ſhould give himſelf up to read<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45648:89"/>he could not be beat off from it, till he was ſo bad, that he had like never to have recovered his ſight more.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. It was his practice to be much by himſelf in ſecret prayer, and he was careful to manage that work, ſo as that it might be as ſecret as poſſible it might be, but his frequency and conſtancy made it to be ſo eaſily obſerved, upon which, one time one having a great mind to know what this ſweet babe prayed for, got into a place near him, and heard him very earneſtly praying for the Church of God, deſiring that the Kingdom of the Goſpel might be ſpread over the whole world, and that the kingdom of grace might more and more come into the hearts of Gods people, and that the Kingdome of glory might be haſtned. He was wont to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue half an hour, ſometimes an hour, upon his knees together.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:45648:89"/>
17. He was much above the vanities that moſt Children are taken with, and was indeed too much a man to live long.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. He was very humble and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and did by no means affect fineneſs in apparrel, but hated any thing more than neceſſaries either in cloths or diet.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. When he perceived either his Brother or Siſter pleaſed with their new clothes, he would with a great deal of gravity reprove their folly, and when his reproof ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified little, he would bewail their vanity.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Once he had a new ſuit brought from the Tailors, which when he looked on, he found ſome ribbons at the knees, at which he was grieved: asking his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether thoſe things would keep him warm. No, Child ſaid his Mother, why then ſaid he, do you ſuffer them to be put here, you are miſtaken, if you think
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45648:90"/>ſuch things pleaſe me; and I doubt ſome that are better then us, may want the money that this coſt you to buy them bread.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. He would intreat his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have a care of gratifying a proud humour in his Brother and Siſters, he did tell them of the danger of pride, and how little reaſon they had to be proud of that which was their ſhame; for ſaid he, if it had not been for ſin we ſhould have had no need of cloaths.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. At leiſure times, he would be talking to his School-fellows a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the things of God, and urge the neceſſity of a holy Life; that text he much ſpoke on to there; <hi>the Axe is laid to the root of the tree, and every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewn down and caſt into the fire.</hi> Every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Child of us that doth not bring forth the fruit of good works, ſhall ſhortly be cut down
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45648:90"/>with the axe of Gods wrath, and caſt into the fire of Hell; and this he ſpake like one that believed and felt the power of what he ſpake, and not with the leaſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of a childiſh levity of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. This was, when he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſeven and eight years old, and if he perceived any Children unconcerned about their Souls, he would be greatly troubled at it.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. After this, his Parents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved not far from <hi>London,</hi> where he continued till that dreadful year ſixty five; he was then ſent to the latine School, where he ſoon made a very conſiderable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs and was greatly beloved of his Maſter; the School was his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved place, and learning his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation. He was never taught to write, but took it of his own ingenuity.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. He was exceeding dutiful to his Parents and never did in the leaſt diſpute their command,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45648:91"/>(except, when he thought they might croſs the command of God) as in the forementioned buſineſs of reading the Scriptures when his eyes were ſo bad.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. He was exceeding content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any mean diet, and to be ſure he would not touch a bit of any thing till he had begged Gods bleſſing upon it.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. He would put his Brother and Siſter upon their duties, and obſerve them whether they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it or no, and when he ſaw any neglect, he would ſoon warn them; if he ſaw any of them take a ſpoon into their hands before they had craved a bleſſing, he ſaid that is juſt like a hog indeed.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. His Siſter was afraid of the darkneſs, and would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cry, upon this account; he told her, ſhe muſt fear God more, and ſhe need then be afraid of nothing.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. He would humbly put his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45648:91"/>near Relations upon their duty, and minding the concerns of their Souls and Eternity, with more ſeriouſneſs and life, and to have a care of doing that which was for the diſhonour of God and the hazard of the Soul.</p>
                     <p n="29">29. He was of a compaſſionate and charitable diſpoſition, and very pitiful to the poor, or any that were in diſtreſs, but his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pity was to poor Souls; and as well as he could, he would be putting Children, Play-fellows, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, neighbours, upon minding their poor ſouls.</p>
                     <p n="30">30. One notable inſtance of his true charity, I cannot omit. A certain Turk was by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God caſt in the place where he lived, which this ſweet Child hearing of had a great pity to his Soul, and ſtudied how he might be any way inſtrumental to do it good, at laſt finding a man that underſtood the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45648:92"/>of the Turk, he uſed means to get them together, which he at laſt procured; the firſt thing that he did, was to put his friend upon diſcourſing with the Turk about his principles, whether he acknowledged a Deity which the Turk owning; the next thing he inquired after, was, what he thought of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. At which the Turk was troubled and put off the diſcourſe, and ſaid, he was athirſt and an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; which the Child being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of, by the interpreter, immediately went to a Brew-houſe near at hand (his own houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far off) and did intreat the Maſter of the Brewhouſe to give him ſome Beer for the Turk, and the argument he uſed was this; Sir, here is a poor ſtranger that is athirſt, we know not where we may be caſt before we dye; he went to another place and begged food for him; uſing the ſame ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45648:92"/>as before, but his friends hearing of it, were angry with him, but he told them he did it for a poor ſtranger that was far from home, and he did it that he might think the better of the Chriſtians, and the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. He would have a ſavoury word to ſay to every one that he converſed with, to put them in mind of the worth of Chriſt and their Souls; and their nearneſs to Eternity. Inſomuch, that good people took no ſmall pleaſure in his company. The Taylor that made his cloths, would keep them the longer before he brought them home, that he might have the benefit of his ſpiritual and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſociety; and more frequent viſits.</p>
                     <p n="32">32. He bewailed the miſerable condition of the generality of man-kind, (when he was about ten years old) that were utterly
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45648:93"/>eſtranged from God, though they called him Father, yet they were his Children only by Creation, and not by any likeneſs they had to God, or intereſt in him.</p>
                     <p n="33">33. Thus he continued walking in the ways of God, ingaged in reading, praying, hearing the Word of God, and ſpiritual diſcourſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering thereby his ſerious thoughts of Eternity.</p>
                     <p n="34">34. He had an earneſt deſire, if it might be the Lords good pleaſure, to give himſelf up to the Lord in the work of the Miniſtry, if he ſhould live; and this out of a dear love to Chriſt, and Souls.</p>
                     <p n="35">35. He was (next to the Bible) moſt taken with reading of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Mr. Baxters</hi> works, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his <hi>Saints Everlaſting Reſt;</hi> and truly, the thoughts of that Reſt, and Eternity; ſeemed to ſwallow up all other thoughts, and he lived in a conſtant preparation for it, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45648:93"/>looked more like one that was ripe for glory, then an inhabitant of this lower world.</p>
                     <p n="36">36. When he was about eleven years and three quarters old, his Mothers houſe was viſited with the Plague; his eldeſt ſiſter was the firſt that was viſited with this diſtemper, and when they were praying for her, he would ſob and weep bitterly</p>
                     <p n="37">37. As ſoon as he perceived that his Siſter was dead, he ſaid, the will of the Lord be done. Bleſſed be the Lord, dear Mother, ſaid he, you muſt do as <hi>David</hi> did, after the Child was dead, he went and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed himſelf, and quietly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the will of God.</p>
                     <p n="38">38. The reſt of the family held well for about fourteen dayes, which time he ſpent in religious duties and preparing for his death; but ſtill his great Book was the <hi>Saints Reſt;</hi> which he read with exceeding curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, gathering many obſervations
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45648:94"/>out of it in writing for his own uſe. He wrote ſeveral divine meditations of his own, upon ſeveral Subjects, but that which ſeemed moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, was a meditation upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Chriſt; he was never well now but when he was more immediately ingaged in the ſervice of God.</p>
                     <p n="39">39. At fourteen days end, he was taken ſick, at which he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very patient and cheerful; yet ſometimes he would ſay that his pain was great.</p>
                     <p n="40">40. His Mother looking upon his Brother, ſhaked her head, at which he asked, if his Brother were marked; ſhe anſwered, yes Child? he asked again, whether he were marked, ſhe anſwered nothing; well ſays he, I know I ſhall be marked; I pray let me have <hi>Mr. Baxters</hi> Book, that I may read a little more of Eternity before I go into it. His Mother told him that he was not able to read; he ſaid,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45648:94"/>that he was; however then pray by me, and for me; His Mother anſwered, that ſhe was ſo full of grief, that ſhe could not pray now; but ſhe, deſired to hear him pray his laſt prayer.</p>
                     <p n="41">41. His Mother asked him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were willing to die, and leave her, he anſwered yes, I am willing to leave you, and go to my heavenly Father. His Mother an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Child, If thou hadſt but an aſſurance of Gods love I ſhould not be ſo much troubled.</p>
                     <p n="42">42. He anſwered, and ſaid to his Mother, I am aſſured, dear Mother, that my ſins are forgiven, and that I ſhall go to Heaven, for ſaid he, here ſtood an Angel by me, that told me, I ſhould quickly be in glory.</p>
                     <p n="43">43. At this, his Mother burſt forth into tears, O Mother, ſaid he, did you but know what joy I feel, you would not weep, but rejoyce. I tell you I am ſo full of comfort,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45648:95"/>that I cant tell you how I am; O Mother I ſhall preſently have my head in my Fathers boſome, and ſhall be there, where the <hi>Four and Twenty Elders caſt down their Crowns and ſing Hallelujah, Glory and Praiſe, to him that ſits upon the Throne: and unto the Lamb for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="44">44. Upon this, his ſpeech began to fail him, but his Soul ſeemed ſtill to be taken up with glory, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now grieved him but the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that he ſaw his Mother to be in for his death; a little to divert his Mother, he aſked her, what ſhe had to Supper, but preſently in a kind of divine Rapture, he cried out, O what a ſweet Supper have I making ready for me in glory,</p>
                     <p n="45">45. But ſeeing all this did rather increaſe then allay his Mothers grief, he was more troubled, and asked her, what she meant, thus to offend God; know you not, that it is the hand of the Almighty. <hi>Humble your ſelf under the mighty hand of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45648:95"/>God,</hi> lay your ſelf in the duſt, and kiſs the rod of God, and let me ſee you do it in token of your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the will of God, and bow before him. Upon which raiſing up himſelf a little, he gave a lowly bow, and ſpake no more: but went chearfully and triumphingly to Reſt, in the boſome of Jeſus.</p>
                     <closer>Hallelujah.</closer>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:96"/>
                  <head>Theſe BOOKS of the ſame Author, Mr. <hi>James Janeway,</hi> are Printed and Sold by <hi>Dorman Newman.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEaven upon Earth, or the beſt Friend in the worſt of times; The third Edition Enlarged, Price 2 <abbr>
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Death <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtung,</hi> a Sermon preacht at the Funeral of <hi>Thomas Mowſley</hi> an <hi>Apothecary.</hi> With a brief Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of his Life and Death, alſo the manner of Gods dealings with Him, before and after his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Drawn up by his own hand, price 1 <abbr>
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Sermon preached at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of <hi>Thomas Savage,</hi> Price 4 <abbr>
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </abbr> A Token for Children, firſt and ſecond part, the price of each 6 <abbr>
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45648:96"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
